<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Demetrius his opposition to reformation. A sermon very necessarie for these times. As it was delivered (this last vvinter) before a great assemblie in the city of London. by John Tillinghast, sometimes rector of Tarring-Nevill, now rector of Streate in the county of Sussex.</title>
            <author>Tillinghast, John, 1604-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E151_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12132</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859222</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859222</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111291</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94352)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111291)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 27:E151[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Demetrius his opposition to reformation. A sermon very necessarie for these times. As it was delivered (this last vvinter) before a great assemblie in the city of London. by John Tillinghast, sometimes rector of Tarring-Nevill, now rector of Streate in the county of Sussex.</title>
                  <author>Tillinghast, John, 1604-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.P. and M.S. for Andrew Kembe at St. Margarets hill in Southwark,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XIX, 23 --  Sermons. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111291:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DEMETRIVS HIS OPPOSITION TO REFORMATION. A SERMON VERY NECES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SARIE FOR THESE TIMES. As it was delivered (this laſt VVinter) before a great Aſſemblie in the City of LONDON. By <hi>John Tillinghaſt,</hi> ſometimes Rector of <hi>Tarring-Nevill,</hi> now Rector of <hi>Streate</hi> in the County of SUSSEX</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. P.</hi> and <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Andrew Kembe</hi> at St. <hi>Margarets</hi> hill in Southwark. 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111291:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111291:2"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVLY VERTVOVS, RIGHT HONORABLE, AND Noble Lady <hi>IS ABELL,</hi> Counteſſe of HOLLAND.</head>
            <head type="sub">And to the moſt Religious, Right Honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and truly Noble LETICE, Lady PAGET, Baroneſſe of <hi>Beaudeſert.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable and gracious Ladies, when importunitie had ſo far prevailed, as to ſuffer this Copie to paſſe the Preſſe, my reſolution was, to ſend it forth under the ſhelter of your Noble perſons; my preſumption herein ſoaring ſo high in the dedication, was not a little emboldned by the generall and conſtant Fame of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours Heroicall and Benigne diſpoſitions,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Laert. lib.</hi> 6.</note> who (according to that of <hi>Antiſthenes,</hi> that vertue and true Nobilitie go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether labour to excell other in goodneſſe of mind, as great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of place. Indeed I muſt confeſſe, when I duely conſider the greatneſſe of your excellent perſons, and the ſublimitie of your unſpotted Honors, I much condemne my ſelf of boldneſſe; but on the other ſide, recounting the magnificence
<pb facs="tcp:111291:3"/>of your bountie, and the humanitie of your Noble diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I cannot but blame my ſelf of ſlowneſſe, in not labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſooner to expreſſe my thankfulneſſe. I have long purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to offer unto your Honors ſome poore token of that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which that underſerved favour conferd upon me by both your Noble perſons (<hi>abſque ullo commerito,</hi> without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert in the world) tyes me unto: the remembrance whereof cannot be buried in ſilence, without the juſt aſperſion of ſhamefull Ingratitude; and ſhould ere this time have been more really manifeſted in ſome preſent of far greater value, if mine abilities would have reacht unto it;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orat.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>azianz. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cra gratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o reprehendi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n ſolet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. c. Epiſt.</hi> 7. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 2.</note> but alas, the beſt requitals that we poore Miniſters can make to our Noble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving friends, for their undeſerved favours, <hi>Sunt verba &amp; voces,</hi> (as the Poet ſpeaks in another ſenſe) are our papers and our prayers, this is all we can exhibite (as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> writeth to <hi>Sophronius</hi>) and this kind of gratulation though it come ſomewhat late, yet I hope ſhall find a candid accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with your Honorable perſons, according to the modell of the offerer, not the magnitude of the receiver. May it pleaſe your Honors to grace this poore piece, (ſuch as it is) with your favourable Patronage, and to let it paſſe under the teſtimony of your pious approbation: I ſhall have great cauſe to rejoyce in your devoted eminencie, and never ceaſe to enlarge my thoughts towards heaven, for the continuance of the welfare and felicitie of your temporall, ſpirituall, and eternall happineſſe, together of all thoſe flouriſhing branches and hopefull plants derived from both your Noble perſons: And this ſhall be the prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors moſt obliged and humble ſervant, <hi>IOHN TILLINGHAST.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111291:3"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL AND HIS MVCH RESPECTED Unkle, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ROBERT TITCHBOURNE, Deputy-Alderman in the Citie of LONDON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy Sir, Beſides importunitie of friends (that ſtale and common Apologie, which by many is made for their appearing in Stationary view) there is ſomething elſe which hath caſt mee on the cenſure of theſe over-criticall times, in the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this poore Sermon; and that is, the unjuſt accepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as I doubt not but the underſtanding Reader, will ſo conceive it to be) which was taken by ſome diſaffected perſons at the delivery of it, who, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſtreete, (immediately) ſo ſoone as the Sermon was finiſhed, were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to affirme, that I were a mainteiner of Popiſh Superſtition, and an hatefull enemy to the Reformation; upon what ground, the Lord knowes; if there be any juſt cauſe of offence given, let them judge, who ſhall be pleaſed to take the paines to reade over this following Diſcourſe, wherein ſo farre as I can remember, I have not omitted any one thing, of what was then delivered. Some few paſſages indeed, here and there are added, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forc't to cut off part of what I had determined to expreſſe, becauſe it was fit I ſhould proportion my ſpeech, as neere as I could to the houre, which notwithſtanding (upon entreatie) were fully handled before another Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in the afternoone, and ſo all that was at the firſt projected, was in either of theſe places (as you finde it here) at large delivered. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which, whatſoever the ſharp and uncharitable cenſure of ſome may be; I take God to witneſſe, whom I ſerve in my ſoule, that in all ſingleneſſe of minde, out of an earneſt and (as I hope) ſincere deſire and tender regard of the peace of the Church, and quiet proſperitie of this Common-weale,
<pb facs="tcp:111291:4"/>I addreſſed my ſelfe to the worke; First invocating the great Name of God (in my private devotions) that it would pleaſe him ſo to ſanctifie mine endeavours, that ſomething might be ſpoken in ſeaſon for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; wiſhing unfeinedly, that all wee, who live in the viſible Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame body as brethren, might alſo as brethren (ſo farre as were poſſible)
<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 15.6.</note> 
               <hi>With one minde, and with one mouth, glorifie God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And therefore I ſhall not thinke I have laboured in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aine, ſeeing I aſſayed and endea voured to have profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it may be with m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, yet ſure I am with God, it is as <hi>Cuptian</hi> ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aketh, (if <hi>Cyprian</hi>) that
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Not the fruit of their Labours, but the affection of mens hearts, gets them reſpect with God.</hi> And yet I am not l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ft altogether hopeleſſe of any profit, that might be reaped by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y weake endeavours, ſince (without any affectation of publick no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or vaine glory be it ſpoken) that which had ſo unjuſt an aſperſion caſt upon it, by ill affected Spirits, with a great deale more noiſe (I hope) then there was cauſe; was yet notwithſtanding, highly applauded in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the beſt able hearers in the Congregation; whoſe commendation (I doube n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, but) the judicious Reader, will better
<note n="c" place="margin">Mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uuntur, ſed mali, Movere, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ite, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lelius ſapi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, ſi duo S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>iones, iſta Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uerentur nunc malis diſplicere lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri eſt, Sen. de rem. fort.</note> approve of, then the others diſpraiſe. Beſides, the much ſolicitation of deſerving perſons, for the making of them more publicke, may give mee to thinke, that they are not (though weake and undigeſted yet) altogether worthleſſe; whoſe importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie I ſhould have eaſily reſisted, (as being conſcious of mine owne mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and withall the great diſpariritie, twixt a
<note n="d" place="margin">Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er neſcio quid latentis <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> viva vox. Hier.</note> lively voyce, and breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe lines) had not the vindication of my Religion and profeſſion (upon ſo foule a ſcandall) cald mee to it.</p>
            <p>Sir, J know there are a kinde of people, whom the Prophet ſpeakes of,
<note n="e" place="margin">Iſa. 29.21.</note> 
               <hi>That make a man an offender for a word, and lay a ſnare for him that reproveth in the gate;</hi> at the leaſt
<note n="f" place="margin">Iere. 18.18.</note> ſmite him with the tongue; Some who are
<note n="g" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.14. <hi>Inordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ati ita ſole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Livius ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nomen uſurpare, de Militihus qui ſtationem non ſervant: Eleganter id tranſtulit Paulus ad eos, non qui ſunt in tractabiles, ut putavit Eraſmus, ſed qui tamen aliter quàm per infirmitatem peccant. Beza in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as the Apoſtle termes them) and
<note n="h" place="margin">Titus 1.10. Of a privat. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Sonat autem quaſi di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s, Qui in ordinem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ogi non poſſit. Eraſm. Vulg Non ſubditi.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, men that be
<note n="i" place="margin">Titus 1.6.</note> unrulie, that will not be brought into order, diſobedient chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<note n="k" place="margin">Deut. 13.13.</note> 
               <hi>Sonnes of Belial,</hi> or (as the word in the notation of it will beare)
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Beliahal deducta ex</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, non &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>al, quod in Hiphil ſignificat prodeſſe, ut ſignificetur in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>itas aſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pernicies. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcat. in Pſal.</hi> 18.5.</note> 
               <hi>Sonnes without profit,</hi> who are ſo perverſly ſet upon their opinions, and ſo ſtiffned in their reſolutions, (though never ſo erronious) that they are ready to clamor againſt any reaſon, that might reduce them into the
<pb facs="tcp:111291:4"/>right way. Yet God forbid, that wee ſhould therefore hold our peace, and refuſe to preach the truth, becauſe ſome will be found to carpe againſt it. It were an happie thing, that wee could all
<note n="m" place="margin">Phil. 1.27.</note> 
               <hi>ſtand faſt in one Spirit,</hi> and
<note n="n" place="margin">1 Pet. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>be all of one minde,
<note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10.</note> all ſpeake the ſame thing, that there may be no diviſions amongſt us, but that wee may be perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde and in the ſame judgement,</hi> that ſo, by our joynt conformitie, wee might all proceed in the common cauſe of Religion, and leade the people in the right way of the knowledge of Chriſt crucified, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> led <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Hebron,</hi> with a ſimple and a perfect heart, (My record is on high) this was the maine thing I aymed at in this enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sermon, wherein I have endeavoured the crying downe of ſuch cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, as might alwayes oppoſe it, that ſo the anger of God, and his fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full puniſhments (for
<note n="p" place="margin">Salvian. Miſſil. de gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernat. Dei.</note> 
               <hi>Ira divinitatis eſt poena peccantis</hi>) that are now ready to fall upon us; may in the uniting of our affections, be both appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and prevented: The Lord make the effect anſwerable.</p>
            <p>Howſoever it prove, I have made bold to aſſigne you a place in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, and in the Frontiſpice of the worke to mention your name, together with thoſe Honourable Ladies, as being a ſpeciall inſtrument in that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, by them beſtowed upon me. Sir, I know your diſpoſition is as free from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aine-glory, as I deſire mine ſhould be from flattery, otherwiſe I could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re inſert a large diſcourſe of your forweardneſſe and impartiall execution of Juſtice in the place committed to your truſt; but you delight not in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, elſe would I give them, my deſire is to be reputed <hi>thankfull,</hi> and becauſe I would (in this) follow the Philoſophers rule, not to tender i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Senec. de Benific. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>in angulo &amp; ad aurem;</hi> I have made choice of this opportunitie. May it finde acceptance, and in any proportion, further you in the way to Heaven; I have no more to deſire, onely in the Apoſtles words,
<note n="r" place="margin">Act. 20.31.</note> 
               <hi>I commend you to God, and to the word of his grace; which is able to build you up, and to give you an inheritance, among all them which are ſanctified;</hi> which ſhall be faithfully prayed for, by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving and poore kinſman, JOHN TILLINGHAST.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:111291:5"/>
            <head>An advertiſement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>COurteous and gentle Reader, the Author of this Sermon li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving far diſtant from Town, and (upon intreatie) leaving the Copie of it behind him, immediately ſo ſoon as it was preached, loſt not onely that juſt libertie (which many take unto themſelves) of altering here and there, (for matter of words) what ſhall ſeem beſt unto them; but alſo of viewing the Preſſe, and correcting of ſuch errors as for want of due over-ſight from thence may ariſe; If therefore you ſhall haply meet with any paſſages not ſo ſeaſonable for the preſent times, as perhaps they were, when they were firſt delivered, or with any miſtakes either in the page or margent. Jt is deſired that you would be pleaſed to make a favourable conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and not to impute that to ignorance, which meerly ſhall, or may happen by means of the afore-named inconvenience. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111291:5"/>
            <head>DEMETRIVS HIS OPPOSITION TO REFORMATION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACT. 19.23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the ſame time, there aroſe no ſmall ſtir about that way.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE bleſſed Evangeliſt S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Luke</hi> being inſtructed by the holy Spirit of God, doth in this book of the Acts notably deſcribe, not onely the perſecutions which were laid upon the Apoſtles by Magiſtrates and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Law; But alſo the raging ſeditions of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Commons. Amongſt others, that tumult which was begun by <hi>Demetrius</hi> againſt <hi>Paul</hi> at Epheſus, (expreſſed in the latter part of this Chapter) deſerveth to be accounted the chief: and therefore
<note n="a" place="margin">Sic Tertull: &amp; Beza.</note> ſome do underſtand it, to be that perſecution which the Apoſtle mentioneth, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 15.32. where he is ſaid <hi>to fight with beaſts at Epheſus, (i.)</hi> beaſtly men, men of beaſtly condition (as the
<note n="b" place="margin">Sic Chryſ. Auguſt. Cyrill. &amp;c.</note> Fathers interpret it.)</p>
            <p>But whether it be this, or that trouble, that happened to him from the <hi>ſons of Sceva,</hi> mentioned, verſe the 14. (as others would have it) or generally (as others) the totall of his troubles that he found at Epheſus, which he expreſſeth in 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Brethren, I would not haue you ignorant of the preſſures and troubles that we ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained in Aſia; how we were preſſed and urged above ſtrength, that we even deſpaired of life in our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:111291:6"/>
            <p>Sure I am, that this ſedition which here they raiſed againſt him, may well be called a fight with beaſts;</p>
            <p>If we conſider, either,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The originall and proper cauſes of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their progreſſe and continuance in it.</p>
            <p>The former of which is expreſſed in the words of our text, and ſo forward to the 28. verſe. The latter from the beginning of that ver. to the end of the 34.</p>
            <p>In the text there are three things conſiderable about this tumult, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin" type="runSum">Parts 3.</note> The time when it was; <hi>the ſame time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The thing what it was, <hi>no ſmall ſtir.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The cauſe moving them unto it, <hi>that way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. For the time; it was
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>(i.) Elapſojam illo biennio &amp; conſultante jam paulo de nova peregri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione, &amp;c. Aret. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>illo tempore, the ſame time,</hi> then when St. <hi>Paul</hi> had ſet all things in order at Epheſus, and now began to think of departing thence, purpoſing to go unto Macedonia, and Achaia, and ſo to viſit and confirm the Churches of the Philippians, Theſſalonians, and Corinthians; and after, thence he meant to go to Jeruſalem, and ſo to Rome, to beſtow alſo ſome gift of the ſpirit upon the faithfull there, and to receive mutuall conſolation of their belief; then, at the ſame time, this uprore began, whereby his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of viſiting the Churches, was for a time prevented. From whence divers things might be obſerved. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The holy purpoſes of Gods children are many times hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of their execution; our intendments come not alwayes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment, though they concern the better things.
<note n="e" place="margin">2 Sam. 7.2.5. 2 Chron. 17.1.4.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> would have built an houſe to the Lord, but he was not permitted; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> more
<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 1.13.</note> oftner have viſited the Romanes, had he not been
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dei juſſu</hi> as <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> and <hi>Theophil.</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it.</note> inhibited: Its a common ſpeech, and yet no oftner ſpoken, then experience makes it true;
<note n="h" place="margin">Pro. 16.9.</note> Man may purpoſe many things, but God diſpoſeth all things:
<note n="i" place="margin">Ier. 10.23.</note> the way of man (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>is not in himſelf, neither is it in him that walketh to direct his ſteps.</hi> We many times promiſe to our ſelves, <hi>Multa magna,</hi> many things, great things, we plot, contrive, and commence them; yet all dies like <hi>Jonahs
<note n="k" place="margin">Ionah 4.7.</note> gouard,</hi> when we ſhould expect their refreſhings, unleſſe the Lord put to his ſeal and ſtamp of approbation.</p>
            <p>Therefore, as it may teach us an holy reſervation in all our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendments, to ſubmit our wils unto God; ſaying,
<note n="l" place="margin">Hebr. 6.3.</note> this will we do if God permit, (and leave unto him the diſpoſition of all our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, ſince neither tongue can ſpeak, nor foot move, if he ſhould
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111291:6"/>enervate them, as ſometimes he did
<note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>Zacharias</hi> his tongue in the Temple, and
<note n="n" place="margin">1 Kin. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Jeroboams</hi> arme, when he would have reacht it out againſt the Prophet.)</p>
            <p>So it may alſo comfort us in an aſſured expectation of the Lords defeating the miſchievous plots of our malicious enemies, he may for a time ſuffer them; but if he hinder the good purpoſes of his own Saints from execution; he will much more defeat and bring to nought
<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 33.10.</note> the counſell of the heathen; and make the lewd intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and devices of the wicked of none effect.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How ſuddenly our hopes may be fruſtrated; St. <hi>Paul</hi> here thought that all was wel; his doctrine had taken good effect amongſt them, ſo that not onely many of the people beleeved; but he had alſo gotten many of the chief of Aſia to be his friends: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doubted not to leave them awhile. But ſee how it fell out <hi>illo tempore, the ſame time,</hi> was this tumult raiſed.</p>
            <p>So quickly can the Lord turn the tide, and make the current of our happineſſe to run in a ſtream of heavineſſe: <hi>When we ſhall ſay,
<note n="p" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.3.</note> peace and ſafetie, then may ſudden deſolation come upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not good to be ſecure; let no man ſay in pride, what <hi>David</hi> ſometimes ſaid in the aſſurance of faith,
<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 30.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>I cannot fall, thou O Lord of thy goodneſſe haſt made my hill ſo ſtrong.</hi> But rather let us praiſe God, both for what we poſſeſſe, and for what we have in hopes, and pray unto him that our ſins ſubvert not either. If our priviledges be more then of late, let our preſumption be leſſe, its the ſafeſt way to poſſeſſe more then we brag of. He took not his mark amiſſe, that obſerved it as an old and a ſure rule, againſt the Atheiſt, againſt the worldlings, <hi>viz.</hi> that
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Totum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte dictum eſt, quod ex partibus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantialibus &amp; quantis per ſe unit is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat. Kecker. Syſtem. leg. lib.</hi> 1 <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> the whole cannot be perpetuall, whoſe parts be alterable; if Schiſme have torn the members, the body cannot be found.</p>
            <p>How many ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> are there amongſt us, who with the wicked <hi>Edomites</hi> curſe the proſperitie of our <hi>Zion,</hi> and gape for the day to cry,
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 137.7.</note> 
               <hi>Down with it, down with it, even to the ground?</hi> We know they have openly and privately aſſaulted the peace of our Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, but (praiſed be our God) they have received much ſhame, and are likely to receive more, for their traiterous and malicious at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts; let this make us thankfull, and not ſecure; as if the Lord could not ſtretch out his arme to puniſh us as well as others.</p>
            <p>Oh, for thoſe poore diſtreſſed Chriſtians in <hi>France, Bohemia, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſia, Moravia, Germany, Auſtria, Voltoline;</hi> who have a long time eaten the bread of unquietneſſe, miſerably wallowing in duſt and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111291:7"/>blood; while we have lain upon our pillows of peace, and eaten the bread of plentie; ah and alas for our diſtreſſed brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> upon whom many bloodly maſſacres and inhumane butcheries are daily committed by the Rebels, while we remain untouched. Let us not be ſecure, there is ſtill a devill, and a ſerpentine breed; who finding that the Goſpel hath given a wound to the peace of hell, are the more buſie to give a wound to the peace of the Goſpel; evermore watching their beſt opportunities, for our diſadvantage, which may be.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third thing conſiderable from the time when this tumult was raiſed, even then when <hi>Paul</hi> was purpoſed to do more good, to beat down the holds of Satan, and to build up the kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt; then, even at the ſame time the devil raiſed this ſtir: ſo that we may ſee, the devil ever deals upon the advantage, when he knows that his kingdom is but ſhort, then he beſtirs him moſt; <hi>he
<note n="t" place="margin">Rev. 12.12.</note> hath great wrath becauſe he knoweth that he hath but a ſhort time.</hi> He maketh uſe of the preſent opportunitie; and ſo recompenſeth <hi>brevitatem temporis, gravitate tentationis;</hi> the ſhortneſſe of his time with the greatneſſe of his tentation; like a malitious Tenant, that perceives his terme to be almoſt expired, does what he can to ruine the houſe; or like a bloody Tyrant, that daily ſuſpecting the loſſe of his uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped ſoveraignty, makes havock amongſt his ſubjects, and fals apace to cutting of throats. It ſhall be therefore our wiſdom, to be the more watchfull, as he is grown the more wrathfull.</p>
            <p>But theſe are not the particulars I intend to inſiſt upon; my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations at this preſent being onely furniſhed for the ſecond part; and therefore we will paſſe from the time when it was, and ſo come to reveal unto you, the thing what it was.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin" type="runSum">Part. 2.</note> St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith it was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>tumultus non medicus, non parvus, no ſmall ſtir, (i.)
<note n="u" place="margin">Piſca. Schol. in loc.</note> maximus,</hi> an exceeding great ſtir.</p>
            <p>The word in the originall to expreſſe this tumult,
<note n="w" place="margin">Significat propriè pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primens natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram ſeditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. Aret. in loc.</note> properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>perturbatim,</hi> or diſturbance, coming from a
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> word which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth a vehement and ſtrong commotion, and is uſually ſpoken of water, when it is muddied and ſtirred.</p>
            <p>It ſerveth here very fitly to expreſſe the nature of a ſedition, <hi>Quae omnes in ſe habet rerum turbas, aut certè bonos viros perturbant:</hi> as <hi>Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>It was raiſed againſt St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who endeavouring the reformation of the Church of Epheſus, and labouring to overthrow their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition; was cried down, by a company of illeterate Tradeſmen,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111291:7"/>Smiths and Tinkers (as its moſt likelieſt by their profeſſion) who had gotten for their Captain one <hi>Demetrius,</hi> a ſilver-Smith by his calling; he with this ratlement being met together, (the moſt part of them not knowing wherefore, <hi>ver.</hi> 32. labour with might and main to ſuppreſſe St. <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine by ſedition.</p>
            <p>From whoſe example, we are taught this point of doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is an uſuall thing in the Churches Reformation,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> to meet with oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it hath been from the beginning; no ſooner was order taken for Gods worſhip and ſervice, but hatred and ſpight fell to the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and lot of Religion; the firſt man that offered the better ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was
<note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 4 4.8.</note> ſlain: the like hath been verified time after time, even till this our age.</p>
            <p>In the dayes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> there were certain
<note n="z" place="margin">Exod. 7.11.</note> Magicians, ſorcerers, <hi>Men of corrupt minds, reprobate concerning the faith,</hi> (as the
<note n="a" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.8.</note> Apoſtle deſcribes them) who wickedly and maliciouſly reſiſted the truth of God, withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> and kept <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in his blindneſſe, by their jugling tricks (St. <hi>Paul</hi> nameth two of the chief of them, which he doth (as
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sic Chryſo. Theodoret. &amp; Theophilact. in</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> ſome think) either by inſpiration or tradition, becauſe their names are not elſewhere found in Scripture, or elſe (which is moſt likelieſt) he had it from ſome private records kept amongſt the Jews, as in their Babylonian
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tract. Mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coth. cap.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Thalmud</hi> to this day we may read, how <hi>Johanne</hi> and <hi>Mamre</hi> chief of the ſorcerers of Egypt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> and mocked him, thinking he did his miracles by ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries, as the Magicians did.)</p>
            <p>This is that which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of,
<note n="d" place="margin">Galat. 4.29.</note> as then <hi>he that was born after the fleſh perſecuted him that was born after the ſpirit,</hi> even ſo it is now, and ſo it was indeed.</p>
            <p>For to omit thoſe ſundrie clamors and oppoſitions of graceleſſe men, which our Saviour Chriſt met withall, when he began the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Church of the Jews, (ſometimes from the Phariſees, ſometimes from the Sadduces, ſometimes from the Eſſens, and ſo from divers others, pernicious Sects) that which <hi>Calvin</hi> ſpeaks of this holy Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> is very remarkable for our purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin in</hi> Acts 17.5.</note> that he could no where erect the kingdom of Chriſt without ſome conflict. And though he were a man whoſe courſes tended all to peace, tempering himſelf in things indifferent to every mans infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; yet meets with tumultuous contradictions: ſo ſoon as any fruit of doctrine appeared, there alſo aroſe perſecution with it.</p>
            <p>Read for inſtance at your leaſure, theſe places, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.8.45.50.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111291:8"/>and chap. 14.19. and chap. 17.5, 6, 7. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8. and chap. 4.14, 15. Experience in later ages hath verified this truth: in thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold oppoſitions, that <hi>Luther, Calvin, Zuinglius,</hi> and others found, who were notable reformers of the Church in their times, and ſweepers of many abuſes and Popiſh errours.</p>
            <p>What our times have and are likely to produce in this particular, I intend not now to expreſſe: my deſire is rather to pray unto God to prevent it, then to trouble your patience to hear it.</p>
            <p>Some Reaſons for it, may be ſuch as theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Becauſe reformation breeds diſſimilitude and diſtance of manners; &amp; diſſimilitude of manners, breeds alienation of affections; there is nothing doth ſo condemne the lives of wicked men exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarily, as doth the preſcribed rules and holy converſation of the godly; like <hi>Pharaohs</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 41.3.</note> fat kine, they make the lean ſeem more ill fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured. And hence it is, that they fall into rage, and fury, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage behaviour, not abiding ſuch as are of a contrary temper with them, no more then clay and iron can weild together. Put fire to fire, and water to water, and there is no commotion; but put water to fire, and then you have a thundring coile: Even ſo, when riotous men and enemies of Gods Church meet, there is ſhaking of hands, drinking of healths, the other pint, and the other quart; but let the righteous come amongſt them, and
<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 141.5.</note> 
               <hi>ſmite them with reproof,</hi> they will be ready to flie in his face.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Almightie God, though he be able and might in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant free his Church from oppoſition, yea and ſo far preſerve it, <hi>as that
<note n="h" place="margin">Matt. 16.18.</note> the gates of hell ſhall never prevail</hi> (nor fight) <hi>againſt it,</hi> yet he will have it ſo, and that for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the better clearing of the doctrine of the Church; oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hereſie makes men ſharpen their wits the better to confute it, the Myſterie of the Trinitie had never been ſo exactly handled, by many of the Fathers in whole Tractates; if the Church had not been oppoſed by divers damnable Heretiques, as <hi>Arrius</hi> and <hi>Sabellius,</hi> and others; therefore as wormwood, though bitter to the taſte, yet good to clear the eyes: So oppoſition though no wayes pleaſing, yet may be profitable for the truth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the greater manifeſtation of the graces that are in the children of the Church; as their faith, their obedience, their love to the truth, and ſuch like; theſe in time of oppoſition, like ſtarres in a dark night, make a glorious luſtre; As in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, when perſecution wrung the Church, Martyrdome gave a manifeſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111291:8"/>approbation of many (unknown) Saints; the vertues of divers had been leſſe noted, if this fiery triall had not put them to it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For the better prevention of ſecuritie in the children of the Church, that the more they are oppoſed, the better they may be armed; and the more ſubtile the enemies of the Church are, to lay ſnares and gins for them, the more circumſpect they might be to prevent them. As the Palm-tree, the more weight is laid upon it, ſo much the more it ſtrives and heaves againſt it. For theſe and ſuch like reſpects, when the Church in her reformation meets with oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, it fals out juſt as God would have it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. Wicked men,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> who cannot abide that their opinions and doing ſhould be
<note n="i" place="margin">Ioh. 3.20.</note> judged of others; they labour to have it ſo, and that for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe true reformation many times leſſens their eſtates; now deſire of gain amongſt ſuch men, will quickly cauſe them to enter a wicked and ungodly combate. <hi>Demetrius</hi> and the reſt of the ſilver-Smiths perceiving (by the means of St. <hi>Paul's</hi> preaching) a dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of their gains, will withall therefore make head againſt it; had they not been like to have ſuffered loſſe by the Apoſtles do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; they would have
<note n="k" place="margin">Calv. in loc.</note> ſit quietly at home, and neither have taken thought for the worſhip of <hi>Diana,</hi> nor yet have troubled others: but becauſe they were afraid of povertie and hunger, they raiſe this tumult, and for their own gain ſake are not afraid to trouble a whole City with ſedition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It queſtions their credits; thoſe places and offices which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they enjoyed, either in Church or State (though with much corruption, yet) gained a popular applauſe, a reputation of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and power; of which, being now deprived by the reformation, their abuſes are made obvious, and that to thoſe who before durſt not take notice of them; this makes them impatient, to rage and to rave, that a whole kingdom can ſcarce contain them, they endeavour to ſet all in a combuſtion; as
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Diodor. Sic. Bibliothec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, lib.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Pericles</hi> who being (not without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert) put out of his office by the Athenians, and called to yeeld an account, turned Rebell, and ſo plunged them into a grievous war.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By this means their lives many times are brought into hazard; their treacherie which formerly they were guiltie of, being now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, is juſtly puniſhed with death, as in the reformation in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthers</hi> time
<note n="m" place="margin">Heſt. 7.10.</note> 
               <hi>Haman was hanged,</hi> and in <hi>Daniels</hi> time, <hi>his accuſers were
<note n="n" place="margin">Dan. 6.24.</note> devoured.</hi> And therefore it is no ſtrange thing that wicked men do labour to oppoſe the Reformation.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:111291:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> Laſt of all, the devil, who (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>is
<note n="o" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.4.</note> the god of this world</hi>) becauſe as a God he reigneth, and ruleth in this world, and the men of this world do ſubject themſelves unto him, as to their God: he would have it ſo, and that for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe hereby he hopes to maintain his own kingdom, he is loath to be caſt out, and therefore rages and foames when he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth any reformation in the Church to this purpoſe; like a bad Tenant, when a Writ of ejection comes againſt him, and he ſees that he muſt out, he will fire the houſe about his eares: ſee how he took on, when he was to be caſt out but of one man in the Goſpel; no wonder then if he rage much more when he is to be caſt out of the whole Church, then he ſtands to it with all his ſtrength, with all his power, as the
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nova gloſſa in</hi> Matt. 16.10</note> Gloſſe underſtands that place in <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.8. by gates, <hi>Omne robur &amp; omne munimentum,</hi> all power and all fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and by hell. <hi>Omnem vim contrariam, &amp; Satanicam omnem hoſtis impetum,</hi> the devil himſelf and all his Angels, all the power that they have, the wicked world, all tyrants and ſeducers, which are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils inſtruments, theſe ſtrive <hi>vi &amp; armis,</hi> againſt the Church in her reformation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Howſoever he knows that by this means he ſhall diſturbe the peace of the kingdom of Chriſt, bring the members thereof into great ſtraits, hinder the free paſſage of the word, and ſcatter the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of his own invention, and for the greater ſtrengthening of this oppoſition, will unite the hearts of the Churches enemies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, joyn them in one, though otherwiſe at variance; cauſe
<note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 9.21.</note> 
               <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes</hi> to be both againſt <hi>Judah,
<note n="r" place="margin">Act 4.27.</note> Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> both conſpire to crucifie Chriſt: the Epicures and Stoicks (men as oppoſite as gluttony and ſobrietie) to agree in one for the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſo diſturbing the peace of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="3">3. At leaſt he doubts not, but hereby to ſtop the happie proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Church in her reformation, perſwading himſelf that with greater eaſe it may be ſupplanted in the riſing, then deſtroyed when once ſetled upon the foundation; this makes him to beſtir himſelf moſt at the firſt, and to take the opportunitie of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches infancie, when
<note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 16.9.</note> 
               <hi>a great doore was opened,</hi> then <hi>were there many adverſaries.</hi> Hence in the primitive Church, thoſe bloody perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and plentie of hereſies, wherewith the world was peſtred: So at the firſt riſing of <hi>Luther,</hi> thoſe ſundrie uproares and manifold diſtractions ſpread abroad throughout all the Churches of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome; and ſtil where the Goſpel of Chriſt begins to be preached,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111291:9"/>and the more purer eſtate and condition of Gods Church endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured; great tumults and outragious ſtormes are more frequently raiſed.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee the reformation oppoſed on Gods part, on mans part, on the devils part, God ſuffreth, man raiſeth, and the devill furthereth this oppoſition.</p>
            <p>The uſe that we are to make of it is divers, affording plentie of matter, either for reprehenſion, information, inſtruction, or exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, all which are very requiſite and neceſſarie to be applied in our times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Firſt for reprehenſion; and ſo it may ſerve,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> 
            </p>
            <p>To reprove all ſuch as are the main inſtruments and proper cauſes of this oppoſition.
<note n="u" place="margin">Matth. 18.7.</note> It muſt needs be (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>that offences come: but wo to that man by whom the offence cometh.</hi> Oppoſition hath been, and ever will be againſt the Church of Chriſt, but beſhrew them who are the authors of it. Would time permit us to inſiſt upon all particulars, there might a liſt be taken of ſundrie ſeverall vices, whereof men being guiltie, are juſtly to be cenſured in this Uſe of reprehenſion, as great enemies to the Reformation; I will onely name ſome one or two. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The covetous whoſe heart is ſo infected with his private gain, and deſire extended to an inſatiable wealth, that (like to our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopoliſts) he neglects all publike good; tell him how our kingdom groans for a Reformation; Church and State is in great danger without amendment; he minds it not, like <hi>Balaam,</hi> his thoughts are ſo fixed on the gold of <hi>Moab,</hi> that, though miraculouſly he ſhould hear a beaſt ſpeak, he will not regard it: In
<note n="x" place="margin">Ezec. 33.31.</note> words he will tell you that he loves God well, wiſheth the peace and proſperitie of his countrey, and deſires that all that is amiſſe may be reformed; but in his actions it may eaſily be perceived, that he prefers his gain before all; what, part with a certaintie for an uncertaintie? If he can keep both well and good; but if not, what ere betides him, he will keep his money, the which by his good will he would carry with him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his grave, and ſo (as the ſtorie mentioneth of <hi>Hermocrates</hi>) in his laſt Teſtament, make himſelf heir of his own goods, he muſt needs be an enemie to reformation, for indeed he
<note n="y" place="margin">Anacharſis.</note> is hardly capable of good counſell and inſtruction (as one of the wiſe men of Greece hath obſerved) he will ſooner take upon him to correct God, then to amend his life.</p>
            <p>Call upon him to leave his covetouſneſſe, he will either laugh at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111291:10"/>you as the
<note n="z" place="margin">Luk. 16.14.</note> Phariſees did at Chriſt; or elſe think you do but mock him, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did the Aſſyrian Armie
<note n="a" place="margin">2 King. 6.19</note>: This is not the way neither is this the Citie, and ſay, you do but diſſwade him, (as the Fox in the Fable did the other beaſts) from that bootie which you mean to make your own.</p>
            <p>Now the leaſt ſuſpition of loſſe, either of profit or gain, by the work of reformation is ground enough in theſe men, of malice and madneſſe againſt it. If the covetous and deceitfull tradeſman cannot put off his ill commodities at a deare rate, nor the oppreſſour buy in his neighbours land and houſes, and ſo depopulate whole Pariſhes, the Uſurer make benefit of his money with the greateſt advantage of intereſt (if not more then) the Statute allows him, but that he muſt be checked by the preaching of the Goſpel: Authoritie muſt curbe him, by more ſtricter preſcriptions then ordinarie, then hee'l have none of it, but oppoſe it what poſſibly he can; deal with the meſſengers of this news, as the maſter and miſtreſſe of the
<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 16.19.</note> 
               <hi>damoſel, poſſeſſed with a ſpirit of divination,</hi> did with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Sylas</hi> (when ſome hopes of their gains were gone) bring them to be ſcouraged, and never left them till they ſaw them in priſon;
<note n="c" place="margin">Verſ, 20.21.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe men</hi> (ſay they) <hi>do exceedingly trouble our Citie, and teach cuſtomes which are not lawfull for us to receive, neither to obſerve.</hi> That <hi>Lydia</hi> was convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Apoſtles lodged in her houſe, troubled them not; their preaching to the Aſſemblies gathered by the water-ſide, and their bringing every day new diſciples unto Chriſt, were no motives to incenſe them, comparable to the loſſe of their private gain: Thus was it here at Epheſus, when <hi>Demetrius</hi> perceived the ruine (not ſo much of the goddeſſe <hi>Diana,</hi> as) of his own gain and commoditie in making of ſilver ſhrines, he ſets the whole City in a tumult.</p>
            <p>But what ſtand we in rehearſall of old examples (ſaith
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gualther</hi> in Act. <hi>cap</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>Gualther</hi>) ſeeing in our dayes covetouſneſſe doth chiefly hinder and ſtop the courſe of the truth: The Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> blinded with deſire of lucre, flie all kind of reformation, the ſame (ſaith he) bindeth Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and the Nobilitie unto Antichriſt, in that they perceive the Popes and Biſhops may maintain many of their kinsfolks with Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall goods and livings, which otherwiſe may go for raſcals, and be fain to labour and toil with their hands: The ſame maketh Merchants, Cuſtomers, Souldiers, and all States of men, offended with the Goſpel, becauſe they ſee, if the Goſpel be received, ſuch trades of waxing rich, as many uſe in theſe dayes, cannot ſtand.</p>
            <p>It was a ſad complaint which the Lord by <hi>Jeremie,</hi> made againſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111291:10"/>the people in thoſe times,
<note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>from the leaſt of them even unto the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of them, every one is given to covetouſneſſe; and from the Prophet even unto the Prieſt every one dealeth falſely.</hi> I would to God the like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint may not juſtly be taken up in our times; that there were not amongſt us,
<note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 56.11.</note> 
               <hi>greedy dogs which can never have enough,
<note n="g" place="margin">Ier. 5.31.</note> Prophets that prophecie lies, and Prieſts that receive gifts in their hands;
<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 56.11.</note> All looking to their own way, every one for his gaine</hi> from his quarter. Such as <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah</hi> ſpeaks of, who
<note n="i" place="margin">Mica. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>teach for hire, and divine for money: while they bite with their teeth,</hi> and <hi>(i.)</hi> while they find the ſweetneſſe and have to feed upon, <hi>all is peace, they cry peace to the feeders. But if a man put not into their mouths, (i.)</hi> ſatisfie not their appetite and deſire, <hi>they prepare war againſt him,</hi> as if he were an enemie to God and man. Oh what abundance of time-ſervers be there amongſt us, which will ſoothe up greatneſſe in errours, and labour to maintain the errours of the times, againſt all reformation for their own advantage, which are ready to embrace any religion, ſo that by it they may procure their own private gain. Oh where is the zeal of the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the firſt reformation, when for the good of the Church, and the maintenance of the Goſpel, they <hi>ſold their poſſeſſions?</hi> What is become of the forwardneſſe of the bleſſed Iſraelites, when they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſo
<note n="m" place="margin">100. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pound ſterling of gold, and 35. thouſand 470 &amp; oddepounds of ſilver, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides braſſe and other things. <hi>Willet</hi> in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. <hi>cap.</hi> 38. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 10.</note> plentifully <hi>to the Tabernacle,</hi> that <hi>Moſes</hi> was driven to publiſh a
<note n="n" place="margin">Exod. 36.6.</note> reſtraint,
<note n="o" place="margin">Chap. 35.23.</note> lawne and
<note n="p" place="margin">Chap. 38.8.</note> looking-glaſſes then furthered the building; the people (for that purpoſe) were content to part both with their profits and pleaſures; it were great pitie that theſe now ſhould prove impediments to hinder it. Yet the truth hereof is ſo apparant, that where men are wholly ſet upon their own private reſpects, they fear not to oppoſe either the good of the Church or the commonweal: And thus of the firſt ſort.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſuperſtitious, who are ſo
<note n="q" place="margin">Longe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſacarnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cina &amp; pietas, Lactant.</note> oppoſite to the reformation, that look what the one erects, the other dejects; what the one makes, the other marres. Its obſerved by
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Weemſe treat.</hi> of foure degenerate ſons. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3:</note> ſome, that Religion hath two extreames,
<note n="s" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Atheiſme and
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Superſtition; between which (as <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> noteth) ſhe ſuffereth in the middeſt, as Chriſt betwixt the two theeves, onely both prove her mortall enemies; the one acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging no good to worſhip any way; the other will worſhip God her own way: of theſe, its an hard matter to ſay which is the worſt, and greateſt enemy to Religion or Reformation, yet the latter hath been ſo accounted, and amongſt other cauſes for theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe Atheiſme leaves a man to ſenſe, to Philoſophie, to naturall piety, to Laws, to reputation, all which are ſome kind of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111291:11"/>guides to morall vertue, though Religion were not. But Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion diſmounts all, and preſcribes a law to it ſelf a form of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which if God will not accept, he ſhall have no obedience at all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe Atheiſme did never diſturbe States, but contracted it ſelf with civilitie and ſubordinate obedience; tumult and diviſion for Religion were evils unknown to the heathen, becauſe they all ſerved one devill under divers names and forms, and for their pettie quarrels amongſt their
<note n="u" place="margin">Mulciber in Troiam pro Troja ſtabat Apollo.</note> puppet-gods, theſe differences were ſoon taken up at a Tavern, and reconciled over a cup of wine.</p>
            <p>But Superſtition is alwayes in garboiles, it hath no
<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Superſtitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne imbutas ani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam quiet is eſſe poteſt. Cicero</hi> 1. <hi>de finibus.</hi>
               </note> reſt, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more cauſing uproares, bringing government into diſorder, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring the confuſion of Commonweals. For proof hereof we need not go far for inſtance; what hath more undermined theſe Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> then the treacherous plots of ſuperſtitious perſons? what more endangered the ruine of the true reformed Proteſtant Religion, within theſe his Majeſties Dominions eſtabliſhed? what hath more raiſed and fomented jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies betwixt the King and his people? what hath more hindred the happie proceedings of Parliament, whereby many illegall taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have been raiſed to the great burthen and grief of the Subject? what hath more endeavoured the ſubverſion of the fundamentall laws of this Kingdom? &amp;c. Then divers Innovations and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which have been brought both into Church and State; partly,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Papiſts who juſtifie a religion that gives way to all manner of rebellion both againſt God and the King.</p>
            <p>Againſt God, as is evident by that complaint of St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> who affirmeth that
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern li.</hi> 4. <hi>de conſiderat. ad Eugentum.</hi>
               </note> the covetous, luxurious, ambitious, inceſtuous, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious, and all ſuch helliſh monſters do flock to <hi>Rome,</hi> to get a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from the Apoſtolike See for their proceedings.</p>
            <p>Againſt the King, by affirming,
<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de Rom. Pontific. cap.</hi> 67. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4 2. <hi>Sigonius</hi> 9. <hi>hiſt. Ital.</hi>
               </note> that it is not lawfull for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to tolerate an hereticall King: they may expell him, depoſe him, (as they did <hi rend="sup">z</hi> 
               <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, of his Empire, making him ſtand barefoot with the Empreſſe at the gate of <hi>Caneſſus</hi>) yea mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him if he favour not their idolatries and ſuperſtitions, witneſſe <hi>Walpole,</hi> Cardinall of Coome in his inſtructions to <hi>Parry</hi> about ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the life of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fifth his ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in defence of the Jacobine that murthered <hi>Henry</hi> the third King of France.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By Anabaptiſts, Familiſts, and ſundrie other Sects; who by their pernitious and devilliſh Tenents do endeavour to cut the very
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111291:11"/>throat of Reformation, and labour what in them lieth, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the true doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By ſuperſtitious Formaliſticall Proteſtants, who are ready to embrace and maintain all that is or ſhall be propoſed, in hope of preferment; whereof if their expectation at any time prove fruſtrate, they endeavour to ſet all in an uprore, and care not what doctrine they prove of, though it be never ſo falſe and erroneous, if by it, they may be revenged of their adverſaries. Like
<note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>Donatus</hi> who when he ſaw <hi>Cecilianus</hi> preferred before him in the Biſhoprick of Carthage, turn'd Heretique. Theſe are ſuch who endeavour to quench the fire on the harth, and leave it burning on the top of the chimney; which will reform their leaſt faults, and let their worſt be marring: who like <hi>Aeſops</hi> dog, are known to let fall the ſubſtance, by catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the ſhadow, whoſe religion is ſo mixt with multiplicitie of ſuperſtitious Ceremonies, as that its hard to ſay whether they be Papiſts or Proteſtants; the too too many experiments we have of ſuch perſons revives that, which ſometimes an
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pliny lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Britannia eam hodiè colebrat tam attonite, tantis ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ntis ut dediſſe Perſis vtaeri poſſit.</hi>
               </note> heathen man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed of the ancient Britaines, that they were ſo ſupendly ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious in their Ceremonies, that they went far beyond the Perſians, (they much exceeded other Nations.)</p>
            <p>Now when all theſe ſhall meet together in one Kingdom, what a combuſtion and diſtraction will they make, by their ſeverall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, one ſuperſtition oppoſing it ſelf againſt another, and all againſt Reformation, furthering the ruine and deſtruction of a common-weal, to the diſturbance of peace, if not to the generall confuſion of all eſtates.</p>
            <p>And thus of the ſecond ſort, to theſe we may adde;</p>
            <p n="3">3. The prophane and licentious, who
<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 50.17. Prov. 5.12.</note> hate to be reformed; and (like thoſe Iſraelites mentioned by the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi>) <hi>cannot abide
<note n="d" place="margin">Amos 5.10.</note> him that rebuketh in the gate, (i.)</hi> the Magiſtrate, who gives publike judgement (as
<note n="e" place="margin">Tremel. Piſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. in por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis exerc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicia publica.</note> ſome) or elſe the Prophet which reproves them in the open Aſſemblies (as
<note n="f" place="margin">See the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall note.</note> others) talk of Reformation unto them, and they will be ready to encounter with you, as the Philoſophers and Stoicks ſometime did with <hi>Paul,</hi> (when he went about to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Athens of idolatrie)
<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 17.18.</note> 
               <hi>What will this babler ſay?</hi> or elſe as the Gergeſites to our Saviour, beſeech you to
<note n="h" place="margin">Matth. 8.34.</note> 
               <hi>depart out of their coasts:</hi> theyle be plain with you you are no gueſts for them; their ſecure lives and your ſevere laws will not cotton. May not the Jews keep
<note n="i" place="margin">Ioh. 2.14.</note> open Market in the Temple, and make
<note n="k" place="margin">Matt. 21 13. Matth. 11.17.</note> the houſe of Prayer
<note n="l" place="margin">Becleſ. 5.1.</note> (Gods houſe) an houſe of Merchandiſe; but that Chriſt muſt come and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111291:12"/>diſturbe them, overthrow their tables, and whip them out. May not
<note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> dally, and take his pleaſure of his whore <hi>Herodias,</hi> but <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt muſt prate on't? Cannot <hi>Demetrius</hi> (here) make an unreaſonable advantage by his ſilver ſhrines, but <hi>Paul</hi> muſt cry down the goddeſſe and ſo hinder his trade? Cannot the proud weare a garment of the faſhion, nor yet the drunkard drink with a good fellow at his Tavern-ſeſſion; nor the ſwearer ſtrengthen his words with the credit of an oath, but that the pulpits muſt ring of it? then down ſhall that Goſpel come (if they can ſubject it) that will not let them run to hell untroubled.
<note n="n" place="margin">Non turbunt Evangelio, dum ab Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium non turbentur.</note> Let them alone, and they will let you alone: but if you fight againſt their ſins, with the ſword of the Spirit, they will have you by the eares, and ſalute you with the ſword of death.</p>
            <p>How may it be thought then, that this work of Reformation ſhould go forward in a Kingdom without oppoſition; wherein (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in every paſſage) ſo much prophaneneſſe and licentiouſneſſe is daily to be obſerved. Run through every particular eſtate and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and you ſhall find by the practiſe (though not of all, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, that I ſhould think ſo; I know there are in every Profeſſion which make a conſcience of their wayes, and in all their actions ſet God before their eyes; God hath his number amongſt us, and I hope it is not ſmall, the Lord of his mercy every day increaſe it, to his glory, and the Churches comfort: yet) of the moſt part, that frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent and deceitufll dealing, or ſome other unlawfull means, is thought the moſt expedite and beaten way for ſupporting them. Otherwiſe how comes it to paſſe that we ſee ſo much briberie and corruption in ſeats of
<note n="o" place="margin">Qui ſedet crimina judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caturus, &amp;c: Cyprian ad Donatum.</note> Judicature, ſuch perjuries at the Barre, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie and unjuſt connivencie in Magiſtrates, Sacriledge in Patrons, Symonaicall contracts in unconſcionable Levites, cozening in bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gains, breaking of promiſes, perfidious underminings, fraud in our houſes, oppreſſion in the open fields, robberie in the high wayes, and divers ſuch: which demonſtrate unto us a generall decay and declination of all goodneſſe: So that in theſe dayes, not onely the ſtate and ſtrength of the world, the alacritie and vigour of the whole creature is much worn; but the integritie which was to be found, even in our fore-Fathers is much waſted; we are fallen into the
<note n="p" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>laſt dayes, perillous times,</hi> (ſuch as the golden age never knew) wherein <hi>men ſhall be lovers of themſelves, covetous, boaſters, proud, blaſphemers, diſobedient to parents, unthankefull, unholy, without naturall affection, truce-breakers, falſe accuſers, incontinent, fierce, deſpiſers of thoſe that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111291:12"/>are good, traitors, heady, high minded, lovers of pleaſures, more then levers of God: Having a form of godlineſſe, but denying the power thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was indeed a time when this Kingdom fell ſo faſt to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit wickedneſſe, that to be ignorant of ſinfull crimes, was held to be a crime (as
<note n="q" place="margin">Geruaſius Dorobanenſis.</note> one living in thoſe times affirmeth)
<note n="r" place="margin">Camden. Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. hiſt. Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum.</note> the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth was full of an infinite ſort of vices, the Prieſts were idle, the people given to riot and looſe life; but pride above all (whoſe wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing maid is deſtruction) was come to a mighty head. Oh that our times might not (as ſometime Jeruſalem did Sodom) juſtifie thoſe times! that our Nation were not the Pontificiall ſeat of ſin where theſe abominations are never non-reſident! but ſuch is the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall concourſe of all kinds of people from other countreys, that all manner of iniquitie by a generall confluence meets here, as the lines at the center: Idolatry from <hi>Rome,</hi> whoredomes from <hi>Venice,</hi> Atheiſme from <hi>Turkie,</hi> drunkenneſſe from <hi>Germany,</hi> the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the pride of <hi>France,</hi> and what not? inſomuch that I ſcarcely perſwade my ſelf, that Sodom lieth in aſhes for a greater offence, then hath been found amongſt us, within theſe few dayes. Whither ſhall a man turn his eye? into what place? what Profeſſion? what calling, and not behold that, which may truly
<note n="t" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>vex his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſoul?</hi> All theſe fight againſt Reformation, and therefore the more and greater the vices are to be reformed, the ſtronger will the oppoſition be.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſt of all, I would to God this work were not oppoſed, and (in ſome regard) hindred, even by ſome perſons, who (I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve) ſeek and deſire it. For obſerve it, alwayes in the Churches re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, there are certain publique perſons, appointed and ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part by God for that purpoſe; by whoſe preſcripts and rules the reſt of the people are to be ordered and governed: as <hi>Joſiah, Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> and others in the reformation of the Church of the Jews, who made a great alteration in the face of the Church, purging the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, changing the office of the Levites, commanding a Paſſe-over: and under theſe, there was an election of ſome eminent and able ones, to further this work (as in the dayes of <hi>Joſiah, Hilkiah</hi> was the high Prieſt, and executed theſe things under him: and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he enjoyned, was done <hi>juxtapraeceptum Joſiae, &amp;c.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Now then if any private perſon out of a forward, though a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governed zeal (as
<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Robert San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon, Serm.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Clerum, &amp;</hi> 3. <hi>ad Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratum.</hi>
               </note> one calls it) ſhall take upon him to reform what he thinketh amiſſe, either in Church or State, (as to refuſe with the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111291:13"/>publique congregation to partake in the Sacrament, becauſe ſome unclean perſons preſume to come unto it; to deny the ordinary ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of it in that regard, (though it be probable that our Saviour ſuffered <hi>Judas</hi> whom he knew to be a thief and a traitor to partake of it with his diſciples) not to bury the dead, to marry with rings, and ſuch like, eſpecially things of indifferencie, which in the judgement of a great
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Omnia in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differentia in Ecclefiae liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate poſita ſunt. Calv. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 17. <hi>Sect.</hi> 43.</note> Divine) ought not to be ordred by one or two private perſons, but wholly left to the diſpoſition of the whole Church; I ſay, for any private man to refuſe theſe before ſuch time as Authoritie, which firſt enjoyned them, have again repealed them: I ſee no warrant for this their forwardneſſe, what is it but to execute and perform the office of a Magiſtrate, and ſo go before them in this work of Reformation, who are appointed for it.</p>
            <p>That fact of
<note n="y" place="margin">Numb. 25.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Phinehees</hi> (being but a private man and no Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate) ſo often objected, in ſuch caſes as theſe, makes nothing for this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>He was indeed of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> of the ſons of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and ſo of the family and linage of the high Prieſt; therefore not to meddle in matters of Judicature, either to give ſentence or to do execution. His fact notwithſtanding approved of God, and rewarded with a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Verſ. 12.13.</note> everlaſting Prieſthood, it was
<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 106.31.</note> accounted to him for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Yet we are to know (and it is the common opinion of the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) that he had an extraordinarie notion, and a peculiar ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of the Spirit of God, powerfully working in him, and prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him thereunto: <hi>Id fit afflatu peculiari Divini Spiritus</hi> (as
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Simlen. in</hi> Exod. 32.19.</note> 
               <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenus</hi> ſpeaks of that fact of <hi>Moſes</hi> in breaking of the Tables) it was done by the peculiar notion of Gods Spirit.</p>
            <p>Now thoſe, <hi>opera liberi ſpiritus</hi> (as Divines call them)
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non ſunt exigenda ad regulas com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munes nec tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henda in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplum vitae. Chytr. in</hi> Gen. 14. and in Exod. 32.</note> they are not to be meaſured by common rules of life, nor to become exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary unto others; they were never intended, either by God that inſpired them, or by thoſe worthies that did them for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore the errour will be dangerous from the priviledge, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of ſome exempted ones, to take libertie to tranſgreſſe the common rules both of life and of laws.</p>
            <p>Let no man think I ſpeak this to quench any mans zeal, no, my deſire is rather to increaſe it: and I would to God that all the ſons of <hi>Levi</hi> were more earneſtly zealous for the Churches pure reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then they are, that ſo the true worſhip of God may be performed without the mixture of humane corruption. But what I ſay in this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111291:13"/>caſe, is rather to regulate and keep us within the due bounds of Chriſtian ſobrietie and our particular callings, that we may not diſadvantage the truth nor this work of Reformation, by an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſtie and unſeaſonable zeal.</p>
            <p>I know there are ſome who are not afraid to ſay (though for my part I deſire to judge more charitably) that theſe men preſume too much upon their own zeal, and through an affectation of ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, preach and commend themſelves unto the people, though in the mean time by conſequence and an underhand judgement, they do not onely give an occaſion of an uncharitable cenſure upon the reſt of their brethren, that they are overcold in religion; but alſo upon the Magiſtrate and ſuch as are put in authoritie for the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that they are too ſlack and unmindfull of Gods affairs.</p>
            <p>Nor is it my private opinion, but the opinion of the learned (whoſe judgement in this caſe is not to be ſleighted) that ſuch men who inconſiderately will run before thoſe who are put in authority to effect the Reformation; may as well take upon them to eſtabliſh Laws, raiſe powers, adminiſter juſtice, execute malefactors, or ought elſe belonging to a Magiſtrate, as to do what they do. The which if it ſhould be granted, who ſees not but that the end would be no other, then a vaſt anarchie and confuſion, both in Church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth: whereupon muſt unavoidably follow, not onely an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to reformation, but a ſpeedie ſubverſion both of Religion and State. For if every man (ſaith
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Si ſuoquiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> feratur impetu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non plane uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as erit, ſed magis confuſio. Bern. in Cant. ſerm.</hi> 49.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi>) ſhall be carried ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own motion, after that ſpirit which he hath received, and do flie upon every thing indifferently, even as he is affected, and do not haſten to it by the judgement of reaſon, while no man is contented with the office aſſigned unto him, but all will attempt all things alike, by an indiſtinct adminiſtration, it will not be an unity, but rather a confuſion.</p>
            <p>God for bid then that any of thoſe who wiſh well to <hi>Zion,</hi> ſhould be found in the leaſt reſpect to hinder the building of the walls of Jeruſalem; what though things be much amiſſe (as I beleeve no State in later ages more
<note n="c" place="margin">See the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance lately ſet forth by the Houſe of <hi>Commons.</hi>
               </note> corrupted) we that are inferiour perſons muſt lament it, ſhew our diſlike and deteſtation of it, both in publique and private, ſigh and pray for redreſſe of it, and as occaſion ſerveth and our condition and calling permitteth, ſoberly and diſcreetly put thoſe in mind of it, to whom the reformation belongeth (as our Knights of the Shire, Burgeſſes, and ſuch like, are from all ſeverall parts of the Kingdom choſen for this purpoſe) but we muſt not take
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111291:14"/>their office from them to reform it; this were (as was ſaid afore) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to oppoſe and hinder, then any wayes further the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And thus have I done with my firſt Uſe, the Uſe of reprehenſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> A ſecond Uſe may be for Information, and ſo it may ſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To acquaint us with the eſtate and condition of Chriſts Church militant here upon earth; it hath evermore been ſubject to oppoſition, no age from the beginning of the world till this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but ſhews as much: if we conſider her oeconomically, while ſhe remains in a familie; or naturally being diſperſed through the countrey of the Jews; or ecumenically, diſperſed through the whole world, we ſhall find that ſhe never had any long ſetled vacation from theſe turbulent ſtormes of oppoſition.</p>
            <p n="1">1. While ſhe remained in <hi>Adams</hi> familie, righteous <hi>Abel</hi> a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall member, was unnaturally
<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 4.8.</note> murthered by the bloody hand of his elder brother, here began the tempeſt againſt this boat and little bark of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo it continued under the families of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Afterward, when farther diſperſt (yet onely limited to the Nation of the
<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 147.19, 20. Joh. 4.22.</note> Jews) ſhe was ſtill expoſed to eminent danger, as in the time of <hi>Moſes</hi> tyrannized by <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> diſtreſſed in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and diverſly tempted, before ſhe could take poſſeſſion of the Land of Promiſe; and then, what with the Philiſtines, Ammonites, Midianites, Babylonians, Perſians, &amp;c. in one day of faire weather, ſhe had an whole yeer of ſtormes and tempeſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſt of all, under the times of the Goſpel, ſince the times of Chriſt, being now enlarged to all the Gentiles, not one or two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of them, but all the world; her oppoſition hath been much more increaſed, being afflicted (as
<note n="h" place="margin">Loc. com. tit. de perſecut. verae Eccleſue.</note> 
               <hi>Luther</hi> out of <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerveth) by a threefold oppreſſion; one violent by perſecuting Emperours, another fraudulent by ſubtill heretiques, and a third both violent and fraudulent, by peſtilentiall Antichriſtians: <hi>Amora prius in nece Martyrum, &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith
<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Serm.</hi> 33. <hi>ſuper Cantic.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi>) her (oppoſition or) oppreſſion in the beginning was great, by the perſecution of Tyrants, afterwards greater by the conflict of Heretiques: but now greateſt of all by the dangerous poſitions and practiſes of Antichriſt in the Kingdom of Popery: whoſe
<note n="k" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Boys</hi> Expoſition of proper Pſalms, Pſal. 110.</note> very Maſſes are ſometimes for maſſacres, and their ſacred ſacrifices offerings of blood. Every one of theſe, like thoſe three regiments which came out of the
<note n="l" place="margin">1 Sam. 13.7</note> Camp of the Philiſtines,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111291:14"/>though taking ſeverall wayes, one to Ophrah, another to Betho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, a third to Zeboim, yet came all with a purpoſe to deſtroy; as thoſe times which immediately followed Chriſt, wherein <hi>Stephen</hi> was ſtoned, <hi>Peter</hi> was impriſoned &amp;c. and thoſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> after followed, which endured for the ſpace of three hundred yeers: the monuments of which dayes, and Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories do abundantly ſhew; how that a man could no ſooner make profeſſion of his faith, but he was either
<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eutch. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. hiſt. li.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 8.</note> maimed, racked, or ſcourged, or burnt to aſhes, or drowned in the Sea, or hanged on the gallows, or ſowed in the
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sulp. Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus lib.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; Tacit. li.</hi> 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> skins of wild beaſts and ſo caſt to the dogs, or burnt in the night for lights; or made away, by ſome means or other, with more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite and more tragicall torments (if that be poſſible) then the <hi>Perilli</hi> of our time have invented, to gratifie the Romiſh <hi>Phaleris.</hi> Surely then <hi>Bellarmine, Sadell, Stapleton,</hi> and divers others of that Antichriſtian ſect, were much deceived in making
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quicunque florent proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ii ſunt vera Eccleſia &amp;c. vide Bellarm. controver.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4 <hi>de not is Eccleſ.</hi>
               </note> proſperitie and outward happineſſe a ſpeciall note of the Church of Chriſt; though <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſay, (whoſe judgement they refuſe not in other things to ſubſcribe unto)
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſque ad hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulifinem inter perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones mundi &amp; conſolatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Dei pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grinando pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currit Eccleſia. Auguſt. de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. Dei. li.</hi> 18. <hi>ca.</hi> 51.</note> ſo long as the world endureth ſhe will go on, but as it were in a pilgrimage, between the perſecutions of the world and the comforts of God: yea though Chriſt himſelf compare her to a
<note n="s" place="margin">Cant. 2.2.</note> Lillie amongſt thornes; not onely for her beautie ſurpaſſing all other Churches and congregations of the wicked: but alſo for her adverſitie, being aſſaulted on the one hand, by the contentious op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Schiſmatiques; and on the other, by the blaſphemous propoſitions of Heretiques, openly wronged by cruell Tyrants, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly wringed by backbiting hypocrites. Theſe as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh,
<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 94.5.</note> break in peeces thy people O Lord, and afflict thine he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage. And this is the firſt thing that this doctrine may acquaint us withall, <hi>viz.</hi> the eſtate and condition of the Church militant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To make known unto us, that Reformation is neither eaſily nor ſuddenly effected: the more corruption, the greater and longer time for the purgation of it. A diſeaſe which hath been long a breeding, will not preſently be cured: how much our Church and State is corrupted, doth evidently appeare by thoſe manifold grievances that are daily exhibited; our pollutions, like beds of Eeles are ſo knotted together, that no leſſe then a clap of thunder can diſſolue them: To prevent Reformation, we have great beaſts and huge bulls of Baſhan, that will be puſhing and goring; ſons of <hi>Anak,</hi> who are ſtrongly ſet to maintain their gainfull corruptions, (as here <hi>Demetrius</hi> his Temples of <hi>Diana</hi>) inſomuch that there is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111291:15"/>little hopes of amendment by a voluntarie relinquiſhing of them, unleſſe the Lord come with a mightie hand, qualifying the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments appointed for this purpoſe, as were the brethren of <hi>Gideon,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. 8.18.</note> each one reſembling the ſon of a King: making them ſtrong and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e like <hi>Davids</hi> Worthies,
<note n="w" place="margin">1 Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. 26.30, 31, 32.</note> men of valour, to turn the wheele of Juſtice upon the back of the wicked, and to ſmite them that ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did the Philiſtines, both
<note n="x" place="margin">Iud. 15.18.</note> hip and thigh.</p>
            <p>Experience, in the beginning of the reformation in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, in the violent overthrow of the Abbies, doth evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently demonſtrate this truth unto us, as alſo under the reigne of that gracious Inſtrument of Gods glory, <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, in whoſe time the reformation was encumbred, not onely with ſeditions of the Subjects, and umults of the Commons, but alſo with much hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying and banding of the Nobilitie.</p>
            <p>It was prophetically ſpoken by that reverend man, <hi>Robert Gnoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> ſometime Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> who lived in the reigne of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and died in the yeer of our Lord, 1253. a man who (as
<note n="y" place="margin">Cambden. Britan. ex Matt. Paris. Anonym. Chronograph.</note> 
               <hi>Cambd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> deſcribes him from the words of one then living) was a terrible reprover of the Pope, an adviſer of his Prince, an inſtructer of the Clergie, a maintainer of ſcholers, a Preacher to the people, a diligent ſearcher into the Scriptures, and a Mallet of the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts. This man a little before his death, complaining of the wicked courſes that were held by the Romaniſts, ſaid the Church ſhould never find any eaſe from the oppreſſive burthens laid upon her, nor be delivered from the Aegyptiacall bondage ſhe was holden in, till her deliverance was wrought: <hi>In ore gladii cruentandi;</hi> in the mouth of the Sword all bathed in blood.</p>
            <p>What crueltie and barbariſme theſe helliſh monſters, have of late executed (and do yet) upon our diſtreſſed brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> is not unknown to moſt of us in this Kingdom, (and all to oppoſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation) I do not ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that either we or they are of the number of thoſe Saints mentioned in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> which <hi>ſhall
<note n="z" place="margin">Rev. 7.14.</note> come out of great tribulation having their robes waſhed and made white in the blood of the Lambe.</hi> Neither is it my interpretation, but
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Marl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> in Rev. <hi>c.</hi> 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>Marlorates,</hi> who makes it a periphraſis of the laſt perſecution of the Church by Antichriſt, which of all others will be the moſt grievouſeſt, to ſuch as are minded to live godlily in Chriſt Jeſus, as the laſt aſſault of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was to the departing Iſraelites, and the laſt endeavour of nature is to the dying patient, (though
<note n="b" place="margin">Veniuntenim omnibus aetati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nec deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt quamdiu durat hic mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus. Aret. in Loc.</note> others underſtand it, of the perſecution and affliction of every age, which ſhall be from the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111291:15"/>time of Chriſt to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>But this I am ſure of, and experience to the great detriment of forreine Nations, hath made the truth of it knowne unto us, that where Religion ſetteth an edge upon diſcontent, there not onely mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinies, heart-burnings, and jealouſies, but alſo bloudy frayes and maſſacres are much to be feared. In <hi>Rome</hi> when the fire tooke hold of the Temple of
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ardeba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti ſceleratis i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnibus ignes, &amp; myſta eſt flammae flamma prophanapiae. Ovid. faſt. lib.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Veſta,</hi> and mingled it ſelfe with the ſacred flame; then was the greateſt miſchiefe done; Even ſo, where the wild fire of contention mixeth it ſelfe with the ſacred fire of zeale, and both burne within the bowels of the ſame Church; its verily thought that ſcarce a river of bloud, will be able to quench this direfull flame. But the Lord of his mercy, in his good time, quench theſe coales of contention, that they may never come to ſmoother the flame of our zeale. And this is the ſecond thing which this point may make knowne unto us, <hi>viz.</hi> That reformation is neither eaſily nor ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly effected.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To informe us of the difference betwixt the militant Church here on earth, and the triumphant Church in heaven; here it is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to oppoſition on every ſide, the covetous, the ſuperſtitious, the licentious daily aſſault it, it is in a continuall warfare, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called the Church Militant; the gates of hell oppoſe themſelves againſt it, <hi>(i.)</hi> not onely perſecutions and ſpeciall ſinnes, but all manner of evills, ſweet or ſower, faire or fowle, of what condition ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ever, as the
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Origen in Math. tract</hi> 1. <hi>Chryſoſt. cont. Gent. Quod Chriſtus eſt Deus. Greg. in</hi> 5. <hi>Pſal. paenitent. The opbilact in Matth.</hi> 16. <hi>Hieron &amp; Rabon. Comm. in Matth.</hi> 16. <hi>Raynold. conf. cap.</hi> 7. <hi>diviſ.</hi> 8.</note> learned well obſerve. But in heaven, nor Satan, nor any other enemy of the Church, can enter there to aſſault it; none of all theſe oppoſers come neare unto heaven, nor covetous nor ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, nor licentious; the Church hath there no diſturbance, no nor yet noiſe, unleſſe it be the Songs of Saints and Angells, and the ſhouts of prayſes, tuned forth in the ſweet melody of Hallelajah, which ſo many glorified voyces ſhall ſing unto God; there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but tranquillitie and eternall peace and comfort within thoſe bleſſed doores; There our eyes ſhall not be dimmed with teares, nor our ſoules ſurpriſed with feares, nor our hearts dejected with ſorrowes, nor one eares diſturbed with cryes, nor our ſenſes diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with paine; There are poſſeſſions without impeachment, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes without cares, length of yeares with ſtrength of delights, greatneſſe of ſtate, without conſcience of corruption, love of all, without jealouſie of any; there men ſhall be good and not perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, truly religious and not oppoſed, happie and not envied, rich and not robbed, Kings and not flattered: Oh glorious Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111291:16"/>who would be unwilling to be diſſolved, when it ſhall ſeeme good to the divine Providence; that he may be tranſlated thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, where is freedome from all aſſaults and oppoſitions.
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Auguſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Dei. cap.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brotus</hi> reading <hi>Platoes</hi> Booke <hi>de immutalitate animae,</hi> caſt himſelfe downe from a Wall, and ſo ended his dayes, hoping thereby ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to come to that bleſſed eſtate, which is prepared for good men after this life. But for all his haſt, his fact is rather to be lamented then imitated; we may deſire the fruition of this bleſſed happineſſe in the Church triumphant, but we muſt waite and ſtay Gods lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for it; poſſeſſing our ſelves with patience (in the meane time) under the manifold oppoſitions, that wee are here likely to meete withall in the Church Militant; And this is the third and laſt thing which we may here be informed of, <hi>viz.</hi> the difference betweene the Militant Church on earth, and the triumphant in heaven.</p>
            <p>A third Uſe may be for Inſtruction,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> and ſo it may ſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To put us in minde, that wee be alwayes well prepared againſt theſe oppoſitions, it is no
<note n="g" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.12.</note> ſtrange thing that happens unto us, when we meet with diſturbances in the Church of Chriſt; <hi>For
<note n="h" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.12.</note> all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer perſecution;</hi> the counſell of the Wiſeman (though <hi>Apochyphall</hi> yet holy) in this caſe is not to be rejected;
<note n="i" place="margin">Ecclus. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoone if thou come to ſerve the Lord, prepare thy ſoule for temptation.</hi> Our Saviour Chriſt being to leave his Diſciples, and knowing that after his departure evill dayes would come upon them, preſcribes them one Petition, amongſt the reſt, for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, which is the
<note n="k" place="margin">Matth. 6.13.</note> laſt in his Prayer.</p>
            <p>I know it is controverted among the Philoſophers,
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſit praeſcire, vel neſcire mala futura.</note> whether it be better to know or not to know future evills; and howſoever ſome reſolve it as a thing unprofitable, yet well diſpoſed judgements have ever held it as a faire concluſion, That it is better to know a calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie before we feele it, then to feele a calamitie before we know it; this makes the prepared heart with more eaſe to undergoe the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and though the aſſault be great, yet being afore knowne, the feare will be the leſſe. When the Prophets ſervant ſaw the Hoſte of Chariots compaſſing the Citie, he cryed out,
<note n="m" place="margin">2 Kings 6.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Alas, Maſter, how ſhall wee doe? Eliſha</hi> anſwered, <hi>feare not; for they that be with us, be more then they that be with them.</hi> The like ſpeech uſeth
<note n="n" place="margin">2 Chron. 32.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> unto the people; theſe both knew before what would happen, and therefore were not diſmayed when they were thus aſſaulted.</p>
            <p>In the time then of our greateſt tranquillitie and Halcyon dayes of the Church, it will not be amiſſe for the members thereof, to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111291:16"/>meditate of future evills, to thinke of oppoſitions, that they may be the better provided for them.</p>
            <p>The children of this world are in this reſpect wiſer then many Chriſtians, who uſe in time of peace to have their traynings, muſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, tiltings, and many other martiall exerciſes, that ſo they may be before hand prepared for warre; the Mariner in a calme makes all his tackling ſure and ſtrong againvt a ſtorme; the traveller who is to paſſe in a ſuſpected way, provides himſelfe accordingly: wee of the Church are to fight a great battaile, to encounter <hi>with
<note n="o" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.12.</note> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and powers, &amp;c.</hi> to ſaile in a tempeſtuous Sea, to travell through a Wilderneſſe of many diſtreſſefull dangers; the greater therefore the troubles are wee are like to meete withall, the better furniſhed and forearmed wee ought to be. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, in this caſe, is to good purpoſe;
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſ lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Offic. cap.</hi> 38.</note> 
               <hi>Gratia praeparandus eſt animus, &amp;c. The minde is to be prepared with grace, and to be eſtabliſhed unto conſtancy, that it may not be troubled with any terrours, nor yet diſmayed with any ſorrowes, nor ever yeeld with any puniſhment.</hi> And this is the firſt thing which wee are here taught, <hi>viz.</hi> that we be alwayes well prepared againſt theſe oppoſitions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It may ſerve to teach us, not to be too much over-troubled when wee meet with them; He that is for Chriſt and his Church muſt feare no rumours, but <hi>in
<note n="q" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.8.</note> good reports and bad reports,</hi> and through proſpericie and miſchiefe, he muſt make way unto him that he ſeeks for, of whoſe name he makes profeſſion.</p>
            <p>This is the uſuall caſe of the Goſpell, He that gave us that bleſſed Covenant, meant not that we ſhould ſticke at theſe conditions; it is enough to have this Paſſeover, though wee eate it with ſower hearbes, and to enjoy the
<note n="r" place="margin">Cant. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>Lillie,</hi> though in the middeſt of thornes.</p>
            <p>Be not then diſmayed with the tumultuous oppoſitions, rayſed by the falſe cenſures of the wicked world; What though the roaring ſonnes of <hi>Beliall,</hi> make ſonnes of thee at their joviall compotations? What though they brand thee for an hypocrite and diſſembler? What though the erronious Courts of men, wrongfully adjudge thee, the friends and factors of hell compaſſe thee in on every ſide, reviling thine holineſſe, oppreſſing thine innocency, neglecting thine equitie, overlaying thy povertie, &amp;c. yet quiet thine heart with this encouragement,
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ioh. 16.33.</note> 
               <hi>In the world thou ſhalt have tribulation, but be of good cheare, in Chriſt thou ſhalt have peace,</hi> yea, that <hi>peace which
<note n="t" place="margin">Phil. 4.7.</note> paſſeth all underſtanding;</hi> which is enough for a man to enjoy, though he lacke the (ill conditioned) peace of the world; for he is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111291:17"/>unworthy of Gods favour, that cannot goe away contented with it, unleſſe he may alſo enjoy the favour of the world. It was a worthy reſolution of holy <hi>Jer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e
<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam ob Domint mei nomen atque juſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ttam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>um turba meſerſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulet; uttnam in op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>robrium meum ſtolidus bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mandus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urgat, tantum ut ego merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Jeſu con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequer. Ieron.</note> I would to God that the whole Nation of the Gentiles, Pagans and Infidells, would for the name of my God, and for the glory of his Goſpell, perſecute mee and trouble mee; I would to God, this mad and fooliſh world, would riſe up againſt mee, for the profeſſion of Gods bleſſed truth, onely that I may obteine Chriſt Jeſus for my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that expects here a ſoft and gentle entertainment (living in the Church of Chriſt) will be much deceived; are not afflictions for the Goſpell called by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> the
<note n="w" place="margin">Galat. 6.17. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Vide Bez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. Annotat. major.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Markes of the Lord Jeſus?</hi> and the
<note n="x" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>dying of our Lord Jeſus?</hi> What are they? are they not
<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſic vocat vincula car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eres cica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trices, &amp;c. Paraeus in Galat.</hi> 6.17.</note> 
               <hi>bonds, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments, infamies, diſgraces, &amp;c.</hi> Yet here is our comfort, they are the ſufferings of the Lord Jeſus; the bonds and impriſonments of the members of that body, whereof he is the head; for his ſake and the Goſpells they were inflicted; and therefore, let us not be over-troubled when wee meete with them; but rather rejoyce in our tribulation, eſpecially ſince it is for our SAviours ſake: the loyall ſubject that ſuffers in his Princes cauſe, contents himſelfe as well in his iron fetters, as the proudeſt Courtier doth in his golden chaine; much more may he glory and delight himſelfe that meets with op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in the Churches quarrell, and ſuffers ignominie for the profeſſion of the truth. It ſhould be ſo farre from diſheartning us, that the more wee are oppoſed, the more ſhould our zeale for the good of Gods Church be encreaſed. Like the Spirit of <hi>Elihu,</hi> being ſuppreſſed, it was
<note n="z" place="margin">Iob 32.18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>as Wine that had no vent;</hi> or as naturall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in carnall men, become more ſinfull when reſtrained by the commandement; ſo love to the truth in Gods children, ſhould grow more fervent, when the Devill and wicked men labour to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it.</p>
            <p>And this is the third Uſe.</p>
            <p>A fourth and laſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> may be for Exhortation, and ſo it may ſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To encourage us, to ſtand faſt in the times of oppoſition and to think never a whit the worſe, but rather the better of our profeſſion; accounting it an honour, that wee are the true members of the Church of Chriſt, though others (who are contemptible) doe caſt contempt upon us for it. Things of good eſteeme are neither eaſily kept, nor yet attained unto, and were there not great worth in the ſinceritie of our profeſſion, it would never meete with ſuch oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Devill and wicked men, would never ſo much band againſt it.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111291:17"/>Shall wee then looſe our hopes of ſo bleſſed a Covenant, becauſe there be ſo many enemies ſtrive againſt it? Shall wee betake our ſelves into the Wilderneſſe, and there live a Monaſticall &amp; Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall life, alienating our ſelves from our worke and labour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee are afraid of oppoſition? Oh, farre be it from us, how unworthy ſhall wee ſhew our ſelves of ſo glorious a priviledge, that will not ſtand to it, and for it, when the Devill and wicked men oppoſe it?
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theodoret. Eccleſ. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>Theodoret</hi> reporteth in his Eccleſiaſticall Storie, that when <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour with his Arrian hereſie, had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtred the Chriſtian world, and ſtruck a deepe wound in the white boſome of the Church, by which meanes the flocke of Chriſt ſtood in great danger. <hi>Aphraates,</hi> a certaine Monk, a holy man of that time, contrary to his order, came forth of his vowed and confining Monaſtery, to ſuccour the endangered truth; and being asked by the Emperour (who was offended at him) what he did out of his Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I would (ſaith he) have kept it, and did keepe it ſo long as Chriſts ſheep were in peace; but now that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts doe come on, and ſtormes bring them in danger; I cannot be coop'd up and ſuffer them in hazard of ruine, every ſtone is to be turned, every means is to be ſought, to free them from this perill. He further addes, If I were Daughter to any man whatſoever, and were confined by my Father to a Cloſet or ſome ſecret cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> part of the houſe; yet if my Fathers dwelling were on fire, ſhould I not be very careleſſe, if I would not then come forth to helpe to quench it, or give direction for it? So if now I ſhould not helpe to teach true faith in Chriſt, by comming out of my Monaſtery, I ſhould doe much amiſſe.</p>
            <p>A reſolution very fitting for theſe times, wherein the affayres of the Church call us forth; God forbid wee ſhould now keep our ſelves within our Cloyſters, and be terrified with the ſpightfull looks of our daring adverſaries. He that would weare the wreath of Victory, muſt not like a coward either abſent himſelfe, or run out of the field, though he ſee much bloud to be ſpilt before his eyes. <hi>Iſrael</hi> had never gotten the promiſed Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> had they been afraid of the ſonnes of <hi>Anak;</hi> the more and the greater the oppeſition is, the ſtronger ſhould our reſolution be. Its recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of <hi>Saul,</hi> that <hi>when
<note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 11.2, 6, 7.</note> Naaſh the Ammonite, came up and encamped againſt Jabeſh-Gilead,</hi> and there indenting with the people, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Covenant with them, upon a baſe and deadly condition, to the great diſparagement of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> It is ſaid the Spirit of God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111291:18"/>came upon him when he heard thoſe things, and his anger was greatly enkindled, inſomuch, that although the <hi>Ammonites</hi> were many in number, great and terrible, and the caſe deſperate, having but ſeven dayes reſpit; yet ſo much the more ſtrong was the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God in <hi>Saul.</hi> and he tooke a yoake of Oxen, and hewed them in pieces, and ſent them throughout all the coaſts of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by the hands of Meſſengers, ſaying to this purpoſe; that <hi>even ſo ſhould their Cattell be dealt withall, whoſoever would not follow him</hi> in this juſt quarrell. It was valiantly done, and like a worthy Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
            <p>Such undaunted Spirits there have beene, who in the Churches cauſe, have ſtood it out againſt all oppoſitions; our bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul.</hi> when he came to <hi>Athens,</hi> a place full of Idolls, yea I may ſay of Devills; in every corner were Temples ſet up for that purpoſe. It is ſaid that his <hi>Spirit was
<note n="d" place="margin">Acts 17.16. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>abatur, Vulg. Irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur. Aug. Eraſm. Tremell. Beza.</hi>
                  </note> ſtirred in him,</hi> incited, exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, (as the word will beare) in ſo much that he was as it were without himſelfe, to ſee that horrible blaſphemie againſt God; and did he not here at <hi>Epheſus</hi> adventure himſelfe in this uproare, when he would have
<note n="e" place="margin">Acts 19.30.</note> entred in unto the people, hazarding his owne life; as well for the maintenance of that truth which was oppoſed, as for the defence of his friends, which were then ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized. The like worthy reſolution was in that holy man <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> who having ſtirred up the whole world againſt him, and perceiving little or no hopes, but that the doctrine of the Goſpell ſhould have been ſtifled in the Cradle; endeavoured the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance thereof againſt all oppoſition, and hearing that the Divines of
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Maſſaeus</hi> Chron. 20. p. 27 3.</note> 
               <hi>Lovaine</hi> and <hi>Cullen</hi> had burned many of his Bookes, by the command of the Pope, he openly burned the Popes Lawes, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretalls, and Bulls, ſaying, <hi>I have done to them, as they to me;</hi> and ſo heroycall was his Spirit, that he dared to profeſſe, that he would enter into that fore-warned Citie of
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyroll.</hi> Anno. 1521. pag. 977.</note> 
               <hi>Wormes,</hi> though there had beene as many Devills in their ſtreets as Tyles on their houſes, to anſwer for himſelfe before <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth of that name, againſt <hi>Cekius</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>Thus naturall it hath ever been to true Spirits, that are guided by the Holy Ghoſt, not to be daunted with perill, nor to hang downe their heads for the oppoſition of the Devill. But what ſpeake I of the noble Champions of Chriſt; the very Heathens were ſo undaunted in their Heatheniſh Religion, that they feared no danger, while they were about their ſuperſtitious rites. As
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111291:18"/>
               <hi>Numa Pompilius,</hi> ſometime King of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> when newes was brought him of his enemies, that they were at hand ready to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe him, put the Meſſenger off with this memorable Speech;
<note n="h" place="margin">Plutarch. Apotheg. &amp; in vita Numae.</note> 
               <hi>What tell you mee of dangers or enemies, doe yee not ſee that I am ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing to my God?</hi> What a ſhame were it for us, if the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhould not beger in us a more noble reſolution, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of it againſt all oppoſition, ſince we have God bound by promiſe to deliver us, when wee faithfully crave his ſuccour and aſſiſtance; and ſince it is almoſt all one (as <hi>Fulgertius</hi> in his firſt Booke to <hi>Thraſimund</hi> King of the <hi>Vandalles</hi> affirmeth)
<note n="i" place="margin">Pene id eſſe fidem nolle aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere, quam negare, uno co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſilentia firmat errorem qui terrore ſeu tempore poſſeſſus ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do non aſtruit veritatem.</note> to deny the faith and not to ſtand for it and maintaine it, becauſe, (as he there reaſoneth) a man by one and the ſame ſilence, ſtrengthneth errour, who through feare or negligence holding his peace affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not the truth.</p>
            <p>And thus of the firſt thing, which this point may move us to, conſidered in this uſe of Exhortation, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſtand faſt in the times of oppoſition</p>
            <p n="2">2. It may ſerve to ſtirre up every one, (to the beſt of his power) to endeavour the furtherance of the Reformation; A dutic be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing indeed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Principally and particularly unto thoſe that are put in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie for this purpoſe, who by their
<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non quod natura ſint Dej, ſed quod officium corum ſit ordinatio div na. Bern. in Joan.</hi> 10.</note> office and
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ob communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ipſis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam &amp; poteſtatem. Zanch. de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu. Deilib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> communication of power, are
<note n="m" place="margin">Exod. 22.8.18. &amp; 21.6. Pſal. 82.6. Acts 23.5.</note> 
               <hi>Gods upon earth;</hi> into whoſe hands, the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hath committed the
<note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> ſword of juſtice, that it may be drawne out of the Icabberd, to wound the
<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 68.21.</note> hairie ſcalpe of ſuch perſons, as are the greateſt enemies to the Church of Chriſt; and who more then our ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ducing and ſeduced Papiſts, the peſtilent diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this Kingdome, the ſworne enemies of our Church and State, the maine oppoſers of an hopefull Reformation. How ſhall <hi>Iſrael</hi> enjoy the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> in quiet, if thoſe curſed <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> be not ſubdued? What ſafetie can wee be in, when ſuch miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants lurke in our dwelling? When Prieſts and Jeſuites ſhall be ſuffered to run from houſe to houſe, and ſeduce whole families? When neither Countrey, nor Citie, nor Court, ſhall be free of ſuch conſpiratours? who have not onely (<hi>foveas</hi> but <hi>foventes</hi>) their holes, but friends and fautors to protect them. But bleſſed be the God of Heaven, who hath ſo furniſhed thoſe Heroicall Spirits (now at this preſent aſſembled in the Honourable Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament) with
<note n="p" place="margin">Eccleſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.9.</note> ſtout hearts, and undaunted
<note n="q" place="margin">Exod. 18.21.</note> courages, that they feare not to execute Juſtice boldly, upon the great and proudeſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111291:19"/>offenders; Goe on yee noble Worthies, with the Spirit of forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, well tempered zeale, and godly conſtancy, to brandiſh the ſword of Juſtice, and to run through (as I may ſay) the very heart of farre-ſpreading Popery, Atheiſme, and all manner of Superſtition; to ſtrike at the very roote of all thoſe abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which you are daily petitioned to redreſſe: Not fearing the faces of men, though their faces be as the faces of Lyons, and their viſages never ſo terrible. What ſhould hinder you in this courſe of reformation? You have the prayers, helpe and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of all good men, the aſſured aſſiſtance of God himſelfe (the ſupreame Magiſtrate) who will reward your care, and crowne your diligence: the Law, Religion, and Conſcience, is on your ſide, You cannot want ſeconds, while theſe take your part. Proceed then (as you have begun) you bleſſed Inſtruments of this happie Reformation; not onely ſeverely to cenſure, but ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to ſuppreſſe, the raging, ranging, and roaring ſinnes, both in Clergie and Laitie. Let ſuch be placed in Authoritie over either, as may not onely by the dutie of their calling, ſeeke earneſtly the reformation of thoſe things that are amiſſe, but alſo may by their well ordered holy lives, be Lanternes and ſpectacles of vertue and godlines, patternes and preſidents of well-doing, grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to all others. That the people by them, as by a glaſſe (even as the youth of <hi>Greece</hi> did by <hi>Epaminondas</hi>) may learne to trim and adorne themſelves with all vertuous ornaments; This, this, will be the moſt hopefulleſt courſe, to rectifie things that are depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to unite things that are divided, to ſet in order and reforme things which had need to be amended.</p>
            <p>Beſides, greater love you cannot ſhew to the Church of Chriſt, more loyaltie to your Prince, more ſafetie to the State and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that it may continue in peace; a greater encreaſe of joy and comfort unto your owne lives and livings, your wives and children, your pleaſures and contentments, than in taking the Romiſh Foxes, and abandoning thoſe Lyons-Whelpes, which hitherto have been nurſed in this Kingdome for our owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, proceeding (according to your juſt Lawes and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Statutes) to confiſcation of goods, to impriſonment, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, or death it ſelfe, according to the quantie of their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; for where lenitie will not recover, nor ſmaller puniſhments worke any correction with them, to move, or remove them from their hereſies and other corruptions, no further clemency is there
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111291:19"/>to be ſhewed, ſince (as <hi>Lypſius</hi> hath well obſerved)
<note n="r" place="margin">Ipſa clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia eſt, in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate malos, non eſſe cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentem. Lypſ. lib. de unareli.</note> It is good demencie not to ſhew any clemencie unto thoſe that are deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately evill. And thus principally unto whom this duty belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>viz.</hi> unto thoſe that are put in authoritie for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. More generally it belongs unto all; every member of the Common-weal ought to endeavour it, and that two manner of wayes, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Privatively.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Poſitively.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Privatively, by avoiding all ſuch things as may hinder it, I will (omitting many others) onely name theſe three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Diverſitie of, Religions, there is no greater impediment to a bleſſed Reformation, then a gallamaphry of religion, when eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man ſhall be ſuffered to worſhip God his own way. <hi>Symmachus</hi> indeed the Oratour, laboured by way of argument to procure a generall toleration of Religion, and thought of no ſuch inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience in it:
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Quia Deus immenſum quiddam eſt &amp; infi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tum cujus natura profecte cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſci non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, equum e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go eſt ut di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa ratione colatur, pro ut quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aliquid de Deo perci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit aut intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat. Epist Sym.</note> Becauſe God (ſaid he) is immenſe and infinite, and his nature cannot perfectly be known; it is convenient he ſhould be as diverſly worſhipped as every man ſhall conceive or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. But he was deceived, and ſo was <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>miſtius,</hi> that laboured to perſwade <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour, that God was well pleaſed with variety of Sects,
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dum ita plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus modis co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litur, &amp;c. Socrat. Eccleſi. lib</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 27.</note> becauſe by this tolleration of divers Religions, he is worſhipped after divers manners: And ſo the Papiſt that ſometime would have perſwaded our late Soveraigne <hi>James</hi> (of happy memory) the great King of Britaine, that it was not onely lawfull and expedient, but alſo honourable for him to permit the publike profeſſion and practiſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion within this Kingdom, (as <hi>Parſons, Allen, Biſhop,</hi> and others of that hereticall crew, have endeavoured to maintain.) But who may not ſee their ayme in this, which is not ſo much to get harbour for their own, as to ſhuffle out ours, and to bring all to theirs; or at leaſtwiſe to ſet us together by the cares, that ſo they may the better work their advantage: Which was the plot of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtata (as St.
<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Augu. Epiſt.</hi> 166.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reports of him) having a deſire to ſet all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in combuſtion, caſt a fire-ball of contention amongſt them, by proclaiming libertie to all heretiques and ſchiſmat ques, to ſet abroach their damnable doctrine; hoping thereby utterly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the name of Chriſtians. True it is, we are too too faultie i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this kind, and whether I may ſay through the ſubtiltie of our ſeducing adverſaries, or through the too much connivencie of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111291:20"/>thoſe which hitherto have ſate in the ſeats of Juſtice, ſuffering the wholſome Laws and Statutes (ordained for the ſuppreſſing of all hereſie and ſuperſtition) to ruſt (as the
<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Habemus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus conſultu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> velut gladium in vagina re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conditum. Cic. orat</hi> 1. <hi>in Catil.</hi>
               </note> Oratour ſpeaketh) like ſwords in the ſcabards, and never draw them forth againſt the ſworn enemies of our Church and State. I ſay whether by means of either of theſe, or (as its moſt likely) by both of them, ſo it is, that if you would ſeek the religion of all Heretiques, here you may find them in this Kingdom; inſomuch that <hi>England</hi> (as ſometimes a Member of the Houſe of Commons in a Speech of his hath of late declared) is like to turn it ſelf into a great <hi>Amster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam:</hi> there is amongſt us a confuſion of religions as there was in <hi>Babel</hi> of languages. Ah and alas, that this Land which hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath been a Sanctuarie for true Religion, a refuge and ſhade in the heat of the day, for perſecuted profeſſors, who have been chaſed like Bees from their own hives, ſhould now become a common receptacle for Atheiſts, Anabaptiſts, Adamites, Fama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, Neuters, Hypocrites, luke-warme profeſſors, and Popiſh wanderers: can he be ſafe in the tolleration of all theſe religions? will the Lord hold any Prince or State guiltleſſe, which permit a pollution of his name? as the worſhip of a falſe god, or the falſe worſhip of the true God, is a pollution of his Name, (as himſelf hath
<note n="y" place="margin">Ezec. 20.39.</note> declared.)</p>
            <p>He is a jealous God, and will not endure any rivals;
<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theod. l.</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> the Emperour when his Souldiers had choſen him, conſulted to have joyned another with him; No (faith he) it was in your power to give me the Empire, while I had it not; but now when I have it, it is not in your power to give me a partner. God will have the whole, and cannot endure that our hearts ſhould be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided between him and another: if we do he <hi>will cut us off from the land of the living,</hi> (as he threatneth, <hi>Zeph</hi> 1.5.)</p>
            <p>Is not our Religion the foundation that even beareth up the whole frame and fabrick of State? and can it be poſſible for a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſtand upon three or foure foundations? Religion, it is the ſoul which animateth the great body of the Common-wealth; and will not that body prove a monſter, that ſhall be informed with divers ſouls? The Church and common-wealth have but one center; every new motion therefore in the one, muſt needs make a commotion in the other: for as one
<note n="a" place="margin">Revel. 12.7.</note> heaven held not <hi>Michael and the Dragon in peace,</hi> nor one houſe the
<note n="b" place="margin">1 Sam. 5.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Arke and Dagon,</hi> nor one
<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> wombe <hi>Jacob and Eſau,</hi> nor one
<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 2.16.</note> Temple, <hi>Prayer
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111291:20"/>and Marchandizing,</hi> nor one
<note n="e" place="margin">Numb 5.2.</note> lampe <hi>the clean and leprous,</hi> nor one
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. Eccle. li.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 22.</note> bath, <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Corinthus</hi> no more can this Kingdom an hotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porch of religions; when one Congregation ſhall be Jews, another Samaritanes, one Papiſts, another Proteſtants; ſome calling upon God, ſome upon Angels and Saints, creeping to Croſſes, bowing to Images, and ſo burning in emulation for their ſeverall ſervices, as fire and water ſhall ſooner agree, then theſe accord in their judgements and affections about a reformation.</p>
            <p>It was therefore good advice and ſage counſell, which <hi>Maece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> gave to <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> to puniſh ſeverally all innovations in matter of Religion:
<note n="g" place="margin">Non ſolum Deorum cauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed quia nova quedam numi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tales in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducentes mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos impellunt ad rerum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationem.</note> 
               <hi>Non ſolum Deorum cauſa, &amp;c.</hi> not onely out of a regard of piety, but alſo for reaſon of State: And
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quod filen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ereticis indixerit. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceph l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>Theodoſius</hi> is commended for putting all Heretiques to ſilence. Aſſuredly the body and ſtate is then ſtrongeſt when the multitude of beleevers (like thoſe in the <hi>Acts</hi>) <hi>ſhall be of
<note n="i" place="margin">Act. 4.32.</note> one heart, and of one ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beware then of ſundring and diſtracting your ſelves into many religions, turn neither to the one hand nor to the other, but keep you cloſe to the true Religion. I but in theſe troubleſome times, you deſire to know which is the true. I muſt confeſſe indeed, that we may truly and juſtly complain with <hi>Calvin,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoc noſtrum ſeculum bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renda quedam ſectarum por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texta protulit. Calvin. in</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1.</note> This our age hath brought forth ſtrange monſters of hereſies; and ſome (none of the worſt nor meaneſt neither) out of their juſt and great ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to Superſtition, have overſhot themſelves, and run into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames. Now it is no ſlight ſtratagem of Satan (as a
<note n="l" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Featly Serm. in</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</note> learned man, yet living hath demonſtrated) to bring us from one extream to another, and ſo by over reaching againſt hereſie and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to wrong the true Religion; as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his zeal againſt the Pelagians, who ſleightned Baptiſme, went too far in urging the neceſſitie thereof, pronouncing all children that died unbaptized to be damned: and how many are there amongſt us (ſaith mine Author) who out of hatred of the Antichriſtian ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie, condemne all Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchy? out of deteſtation of ſuperſtitious rites, diſlike even decent ceremonies? in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to gariſh and idolatrous trimming of Temples, are brought to diſallow all coſt in adorning and beautifying Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. This is not the truth: <hi>In medio conſiſtit veritas;</hi> errours in doctrine may be in both extreames, and truth in the middle. As men therefore when they paſſe over a narrow bridge, if they be be not exceeding carefull, when the body ſwayeth, or the foot ſlippeth one way, by haſtily leaning too far the other, they may
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111291:21"/>irrecoverably fall; therefore the
<note n="m" place="margin">Medio tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſinius this.</note> middle way is the ſafeſt. Even ſo in this caſe. <hi>Tertullian</hi> (to find out the true Religion) would have us fix our eyes upon that
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quod Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia ab Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, Apoſtoli à Chriſte, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus à D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t. Tertul. de praeſcript. ca.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 37.</note> which the Church hath received from the Apoſtles, the Apoſtles from Chriſt, and Chriſt from God. This was that which our Church of <hi>England</hi> reſolved upon in her firſt reformation, in the dayes of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, when for the avoiding of diverſities of opinions, and for the ſtabliſhing of conſent touching true Religion, thoſe 39. Articles of our Church were agreed upon. To theſe (though happily by ſome in theſe dayes conteſted againſt) let us ſtill ſubſcribe, if we deſire a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of thoſe corruptions that are now crept into our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And this is the firſt thing we muſt avoid, diverſitie of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Diviſion of hearts, a true effect of diverſitie of Religions, and not onely a great impediment to Reformation, but an open gap to confuſion; the enemie having thereby a greater advantage to work his purpoſe. For it hath ever been the wilineſſe of Satan, to make firſt a diviſion in the Church, and then ſingly to ſet upon her, that he may the eaſier make his conqueſt upon a part, then the whole; as the laſt of the <hi>Horatii</hi> dealt with the two <hi>Curatii</hi> in the
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Addito ad virtutem dolo ut diſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aberet hoſte ſimulat fugam, ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſque (prout ſequi poteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) adortus exupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Flor. li.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Romane</hi> ſtorie; the manner whereof by
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Livi. Decad.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Livie</hi> is thus at large deſcribed. It being agreed by both Armies of the <hi>Romanes</hi> and the <hi>Albanes,</hi> for the ſparing of much blood-ſhed, to put the triall of all to the iſſue of a battell, between ſix brethren, three on the one ſide the ſons of <hi>Curatius,</hi> and three on the other ſide the ſons of <hi>Horatius;</hi> while the <hi>Curatii</hi> were united, though they were all three ſorely wounded, they killed two of the <hi>Horatii;</hi> the third re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining though not hurt at all yet finding himſelf not able to make his partie good againſt all three, begins to take his heers, and when he ſaw them follow him ſlowly, one after the other as they were able, by reaſon of their heavie armour and ſore wounds he fals upon them one after another, and ſlayes them all three. Even ſo, the devill aſſau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts not this body while it is healthy and ſtrong, as long as the parts are nearly compacted and condenſated by cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; but like a wily enemie, takes advantage by ſome dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous breach, and enters through the disbanded troopes of our armies.</p>
            <p>Diviſions have evermore been an enemie unto any good work, eſpecially to this of Reformation; how ſhould our adverſaries be ever perſwaded to accord with us, when we cannot agree
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111291:21"/>amongſt our ſelves? will not they boaſt the goodneſſe of their errours, whileſt we differ in our truth? and be deterr'd from our communion, when they ſhall ſee and behold our diſſention? One of the maine arguments whereby
<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 34.21,</note> 
               <hi>Hamor</hi> and <hi>Shechem</hi> went about to perſwade their people to entertain <hi>Jacob</hi> and his familie, and their Religion, was, becauſe <hi>they were peaceable:</hi> the very Heathen will condemne what we profeſſe, as untrue and unwarrantable;
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quia omnis ſecta Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſmi titulos ſibi vendicat, tamen alia ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am execratur &amp; condemnat, Clement. Alex. Stromat. l.</hi> 7.</note> when every ſect challenging to it ſelf the title and right of true Chriſtianitie, ſhall yet nevertheleſſe one curſe and condemne another.</p>
            <p>It is a militarie principle, Tempt not an enemie by giving him the advantage: what is this but to hearten their malignant oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to aſſault us, when they ſpie a breach amongſt us?
<note n="t" place="margin">Anximus Philippum no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ipſi Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſes.</note> The <hi>Athenians</hi> complained, that they had ſtrengthened King <hi>Philip</hi> againſt themſelves, by their own contentions: and ſo may we, our own ſeditions have been our enemies gains, broken down the walls of <hi>Sion,</hi> and betrayed the peace of our <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> and how indeed can it be otherwiſe, when as the diſſolving the union of parts, is the overthrowing the unitie of the whole. Tis ſo in other bodies,
<note n="v" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Naz. orat.</hi> 12. <hi>p.</hi> 198.</note> every part of the world ſubſiſting by a peaceable temper, and diſſolving by the contrary: ſo true is that maxime in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie, in all States and Societies, <hi>Omne diviſibile eſt corruptibile.</hi> In the body of a man, ſo long as the humours are at a fair agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, choller proportionably allaid with fleagme, and the ſprightfull blood ballaſt with melancholly, the whole is preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the harmony of its parts; the perfect
<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Connexi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> totius corporis unam ſanita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem unam pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chritudinem facit. Leo E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 84, <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> joyning of each to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, cauſeth one health to bleſſe it, and one beautie to grace the whole compoſure of it; but when theſe are ſtriving one with another, when the blood and the choller are one againſt another, then there is an evidence and open ſigne and overture of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; there being as it were all the banners of nature diſplayed, to deſtroy it ſelf. Even ſo in the Church of God, when one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhall ſtrive and fight againſt another, learned men ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt learned men; one Proteſtant Preacher ſet to diſpute that which another teacheth, and to pull down that which ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buildeth: to wrangle and jangle not ſo much (it may be) about fundamentals, as trifles, meere unneceſſarie ſuperſtitions, a conſent (perhaps) of opinions in contrarie termes, (as
<note n="x" place="margin">1 <hi>Sent. d.</hi> 11. <hi>q.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Scotus</hi> cenſures the difference betwixt the Eaſterne and Weſterne Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches) for a little meat and for dayes, (as the Church of
<note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 14 5.15,</note> 
               <hi>Rome</hi> was
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111291:22"/>grievouſly diſtracted, great ſtirs were raiſed (as afterwards by <hi>Victor</hi> Biſhop thereof) about the uſe of leavened and unleavened bread, as
<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb li.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> teſtifieth) the like contentions about things indifferent, do trouble the
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Angli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as quoque &amp; Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſias ſim. lecerta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n de re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoris in hanc uſque diem exerc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeus in Rom. cap.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Churches to this day; about ſitting and kneeling, about black and white, (as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Conſtantinopolitanes did in the dayes of <hi>Juſtinian</hi> about blew and greene, till (as one ſaith) they were all neither blew not greene, the ſlain ſwimming in blood, and the Emperour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf endangered. So the factions of the <hi>Bianchi</hi> and <hi>Neri</hi> about the two colours of black and white, coſt the Dukedome of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> deare, even the beauty and peace of the Countrey.)</p>
            <p>This of all others is moſt dangerous, and a fore-runner of a great and fearfull calamity that muſt befall the whole houſe. Thus I was in <hi>Grecce,</hi> but when? even a little before it came to rume. It is our Saviours axiome,
<note n="b" place="margin">Mark 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>A Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand:</hi> the building is much endangered to ruine when the ſtones ſquare and jarre one with another. Needs muſt the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Iſrael be diſquieted, and her peace diſturbed, when ſuch op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites, like <hi>Rebeckahs twins</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> ſtruggle in her wombe. If the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction of voices hindred the building of Babel, will not diviſion of hearts hinder the building of Jeruſalem? Miſerable experience hath made it manifeſt, to the great detriment of ſundrie Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that diſunion follows, where diſtraction went before. The diviſion amongſt the Troians, made way for the Grecians; the Grecians being divided, <hi>Philip</hi> was brought in: The diviſion of the Aſſyrian Monarchie, brought in the Perſians; of the Perſian, brought in the Macedonian; of the Macedonian brought in the Romane; of the Romane brought in the Turke; which unclean bird ſhould never have rooſted in thoſe ſanctified Dominions, <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſhould never have been worſhipped, where once the Arke ſtood; had <hi>Iſrael</hi> been true to <hi>Judah,</hi> but the renting of the ten Tribes from the two, hath made both the two and the ten miſerable.</p>
            <p>Diviſions in the Church do uſually lead to a diſturbance in the State, and ſo both fighting one againſt another, untill at length an utter extirpation devour and ſwallow all. Oh the unhappines of civill diſſentions! The
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gallo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um decies centum millia cecide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt Eccleſiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> 20. <hi>millia fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſa. Collignius.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>French</hi> our neighbours, can ſpeak it by experience, in whoſe late civill wars there were no leſſe in ten yeers ſpace, then ten hundred thouſand men conſumed, twentie thouſand Churches overthrown. Our own home-bred garboiles
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111291:22"/>are yet freſh upon record, in thoſe diſtracted times of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth, betwixt the Houſes of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>Yorke,</hi> in which unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie quarrell before they were united, there were cruelly butchered an hundred thouſand men (as
<note n="e" place="margin">Pont. Heute.</note> one ſaith) ten thouſand families (as
<note n="f" place="margin">Comineus.</note> another) were rooted out, and fourſcore Princes of the blood Royall, put to death; inſomuch, that no man can but marvell (ſaith
<note n="g" place="margin">Sic Comine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ut nullus non execretur &amp; admiretur crudelitatem &amp; barbaram inſaniam quae inter bomines eodem ſub cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo natos, ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem linguae ſanguinis reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis exerca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur.</note> one) at that barbarous immanitie and ferall madneſſe, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted betwixt men of the ſame Nation, language, and Religion.</p>
            <p>In a word, they that have been leaſt endamaged, have but little cauſe to joy in it: the Lord bleſſe this Nation from it, rather let it befall the enemies of God and his Church, that <hi>they may be
<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 49.26.</note> fed with their own fleſh, and made drunken with their own blood, as with new wine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for us let there be no
<note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10.</note> diviſions amongſt us; but let us be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly joyned together <hi>in the ſame mind and in the ſame judgement.
<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 133.1.</note> Behold, how good and how pleaſant a thing it is for brethren to dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in unitie!</hi> when <hi>inter multa corpora non multa corda</hi> (as
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. in Pſal.</hi> 133.</note> 
               <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſpeaketh) amongſt divers men, there are not divers minds: It is precious as the <hi>oyntment of Aaron,</hi> and profitable <hi>as the dew of Hermon;</hi> the Lord make this dewe abundantly to fall about the Tents of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſweet agreement amongſt our ſelves, is (as
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoc praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium eſt reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis noſtre caput. Calvin in</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith) the main head of our Religion; upon this
<note n="n" place="margin">Hoc etiam conſenſu ſtat &amp; ſubmixa eſt ſalus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae. Calv. ib.</note> rock the health and ſafetie of the Church is founded and ſetled; if therefore we deſire to further the reformation of it, from ſuch corruptions and abuſes as are in it, let us beware of theſe diviſions: which is the ſecond thing we muſt endeavour to avoid.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Diſſenſion about teachers, which ordinarily effecteth a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of hearts, and ſo makes a moſt dangerous rent and breach in the Church of Chriſt; Some are ſo wiſe, that they care for no Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s at all, no mans gift likes them, nor yet any mans labour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails with them: like the
<note n="o" place="margin">Matth. 11.18.19.</note> Jews, though <hi>John</hi> came in one ſort, and Chriſt in another; yet neither <hi>John</hi> nor Chriſt could pleaſe them.</p>
            <p>Others are ſo wilfull that ſuch an one ſhall teach them, and no body elſe, none comparable unto him: and they that do not hear him, are not worthy (in their judgements) to be accounted Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors.</p>
            <p>The refractorie will hear none but refuſers of conformitie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denming all others that ſhall ſubſcribe and interpoſe themſelves for the Churches peace, as time-ſervers, enemies to all goodneſſe, men
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111291:23"/>of prophane minds, haters of Religion, deſpiſers of the Word, and ſuch as would be as forward for the Maſſe, as the Communion, if the State ſhould alter; on the contrary, the conformiſt will not hear them as do not ſuit with him in every point, flouting and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riding them under the name of Puritans, Brethren, Preciſians, and ſuch like. The licentious and corrupt liver, he likes none but ſuch <hi>as will
<note n="p" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.4.</note> run into the ſame exceſſe of riot with him,</hi> drink, and ſweare, and drab, as he doth; preach to his Pariſhioners in the <hi>Lycaonian</hi> language <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Omnia bene,</hi> every thing is as it ſhould be, when God knows all is ſtarke naught; unleſſe he will
<note n="q" place="margin">Ezek. 13.18</note> 
               <hi>ſewe pillows</hi> (where indeed he ſhould rather quilt thorns) and proclaim
<note n="r" place="margin">Ier. 8.11. Ezek. 13.10.</note> peace, peace, in ſtead of war, and
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Prov. 24.24.</note> ſay to the wicked, thou art righteous; he is no Parſon for him: let him
<note n="t" place="margin">Micah 2.11. Iſa. 56.12.</note> 
               <hi>prophecie of wine and of ſtrong drink,</hi> and he ſhall be a Prophet for theſe men. Others again eſteem of none, but ſuch as are excellently endowed with more then ordinary gifts both of nature and grace; to him they will flock, and him they will admire: but if a man of leſſe eminencie and meaner parts, be in place, (though approved of by the Church, and one who is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable in his way, diligent and painfull in the employment of that talent which is committed unto him, for his Maſters advantage, of an holy life and converſation) yet, they will not vouchſafe to hear him: he is either of a ſlowe voice, or elſe of a bad memorie, he looks too much on his book, his method pleaſeth them not, nor yet ſometimes his doctrine; ſome ſay he preaches too much mercy, others too much judgement (as if he knew not
<note n="u" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>rightly how to divide the word of truth</hi>) and ſo one way or other he is not for their tooth.</p>
            <p>Now this muſt needs breed a great diſtraction and unorderly confuſion in the Church, when ſome ſhall be extolled, others ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and others deſpiſed, it works much upon the contemned part, ſtirs them up to anger, provokes them to diſcontent, ſettles them in malice, incites them to envie: All which are grounded upon contempt (as the
<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſtot. li.</hi> 2. <hi>Reſt. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>ubi ira ſic dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficitur.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Philoſopher ſheweth) nothing being at any time taken offenſively, but <hi>ſub ratione contemptus;</hi> when men ſhall be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by others, as if they were not, and have no reckoning at all made of them, as if they were not worth the whiſtling after, in reſpect of others (to whom it may be they are no wayes inferiour in regard of ſome other graces of the Spirit) this I ſay is grievous to their nature, makes them many times prefer greater inconveniences before it (as he in the
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Satius eſt mibi quovis exitia interire &amp;c. Plaut. in Ciſtel. Act.</hi> 4. <hi>Scen.</hi> 3.</note> Comedie, who had rather be baniſhed,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111291:23"/>then derided or contemned) this exaſperates mens thoughts, makes them impatient one of another, drives every ſide upon a peculiar bottome, and ſo procures an inſeparable diviſion amongſt them.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> though otherwiſe a renowned Church,
<note n="y" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus;
<note n="z" place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> confirmed in Chriſt,
<note n="a" place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note> called unto the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Sonne of God;</hi> yet are blamed by the Apoſtle for theſe
<note n="b" place="margin">Verſ. 11.12.</note> contentions amongſt them.</p>
            <p>They had three famous Preachers, men of extraordinary worth and great eminency in the Church.</p>
            <p>There was S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> who for his learning, zeale, ſanctification, miraculous converſion, fiery devotion, though he were <hi>Noviſſimus Apoſtolorum in ordine,</hi> yet he was <hi>Primus in merito,</hi> being rapt up into the heavens, where he learned Divinitie amongſt the Angells in the Schoole of Paradiſe, under the tuition of God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>There was <hi>Apollo,</hi> who was borne at
<note n="c" place="margin">Acts 18.24.</note> 
               <hi>Alexandria,</hi> powerfull in the Scriptures, fervent in Spirit, received amongſt the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, after ſome inſtructions from <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> teaching Chriſt eloquently, and powerfully, and refuteth his enemies boldly.</p>
            <p>There was <hi>Cephas,</hi> who (as
<note n="d" place="margin">Jerom. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talog. Script.</note> 
               <hi>Jerome</hi> ſtiles him) was <hi>Princeps A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolum,</hi> or (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> calls him)
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Supremus praecipuus, ſive ſupremum lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum obtinens. Excellentiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſive E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minentiſſimus, apud Herodia. lib.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Primate and chiefe of the Apoſtles, either for the priviledge of his age, or the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of his ſpeech, or honours conferd upon him by our Saviour, as chooſing him for his individuall companion in raiſing the dead, in his transfiguration on the Mount, in his laſt Vigils in the garden; his ſpeech alwayes directed to him, as a perſon repreſenting the reſt, his favourite and darling, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>All of them (no doubt) men of grace and excellent gifts, though not all of one ſort; and through this diverfitie, the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> falls into as great diſtemper; Some will be for <hi>Paul,</hi> profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves to be onely his followers; others for <hi>Apollo,</hi> mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying his powerfull Eloquence, and ſlighting <hi>Pauls</hi> plainneſſe; others for none of them both, but onely for <hi>Cephas;</hi> they will goe heare him, he goes beyond the other two. Now theſe diſſentions amongſt them about their Paſtours, did not onely hinder the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles proceedings, who was to impart unto them ſome great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries; but alſo hatcht contentions in their ſecular affaires; as may eaſily be ſeene by his gradation, <hi>cap.</hi> 3.3. there being amongſt them
<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>envying, and ſtrife, and diviſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame effects hath this diſſention wrought in other Churches;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111291:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:111291:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:111291:25"/>What it may doe in ours, may eaſily be perceived, if in ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable time it be not amended.</p>
            <p>All you then that deſire an happy proceeding in the reformation, avoyd this diſſention. You that are Non-conformiſts, deſpiſe not them who have willingly ſubſcribed, (I doe not ſay, like thoſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gelaſ. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zic. part.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>Arrian</hi> Biſhops, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, onely with their hands, but not with their hearts; but ſuch as have freely and chearfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) It is no impoſſibilitie for ſuch men to be good and honeſt, and religious and zealous men too, yea and to lay downe their lives for the teſtimony of Gods truth, and for the maintenance of the Goſpell, if they ſhould be thereunto called; as many ſuch in this Kingdome did, both Biſhops and conformable Miniſters in the dayes of Queene <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you that are Conformiſts, neglect not to heare them, who refuſe ſubſcription; there be of that part alſo, good and honeſt men, of unreproveable converſation, who have upright and ſincere hearts to God-ward, who are unfeinedly zealous of his truth, in the maintenance of pure Religion, there may be
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sanctiſtante charitate poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt errare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam contra Catholi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am veritatem. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cham. Dial. part.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> errour in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in both; both ſubject to infirmitie, and therefore let neither be deſpiſed more then either. Keepe you cloſe to your owne Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours (eſpecially at ſuch times when they give their attendance within the doores of the Lords Sanctuary,
<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> watching for your ſoules) though their gifts be farre inferiour, and come much ſhort of the gifts of many others; yet they <hi>are they that muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of you unto God.</hi> Beſides, all the Lords ſervants in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, are not alike endowed; ſome have
<note n="k" place="margin">Math. 25.15.</note> 
               <hi>five talents, ſome but two,</hi> ſome but one; ſome have a more excellent gift of conference, ſome of prayer, ſome of exhortation, ſome in opening of a Text, ſome in application, &amp;c. and yet all are Gods faithfull ſervants, and have their gifts given them <hi>to
<note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.7.</note> profit withall,</hi> and from any of their gifts,
<note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.31.</note> all may learne and get profit, if the fault be not their owne. He that hath the meaneſt, (being truly ſanctified,) may yet conferre <hi>aliquid in publicam,</hi> caſt his gift ſuch as it is into the common treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Church; which may ſome way or other be profitable unto Gods people, and helpe on-ward the edification of thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his charge (as I have
<note n="n" place="margin">In a Sermon preached at a Viſitation, holden at St. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>haels</hi> Church in <hi>Lewes</hi> Aprill the ninth 1638.</note> elſewhere declared.)</p>
            <p>Phyſitians ſay, that the Conſtitutions of all mens bodies, are of a mixture of hot, dry, cold, and moiſt, and yet the wiſdome of God hath ſo diverſly tempered theſe, that ſcarce in the world are two men to be found, in every point of the like temper; The face of man
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111291:25"/>is not above a ſpan over, yet let ten thouſand men be together, and their countenances ſhall all differ: So in the Church, let diverſe men Preach of the ſame Text, and all ſoundly and to the point; yet ſcarce two of an hundred to be found, that have in all things the like gift, either of matter or utterance (therefore it was to the amazement and admiration of <hi>Ptolomie,</hi> that the Seventie Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, being placed in ſundry roomes, never conferring and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another, did yet upon the ſame Text, write the ſame thing, not onely for ſence of matter, but even for ſound of words (as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> reports) but this is the ſame <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>That manifold wiſedome of God,</hi> that liking not one, wee may like another, and the varietie of mens affections be ſatisfied with the varietie of his gifts. Accord then in this particular, doe not abuſe this great mercy, contemne none for the meanneſſe of his gifts (if truly ſanctified) but make a good uſe of all, that by ſome one or other of them, you may be throughly reformed, and ſo brought from all your ſinnes unto God. And this is the laſt impediment which muſt be avoyded, if we deſire the furtherance of the Reformation, <hi>viz.</hi> diſſention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Teachers.</p>
            <p>And thus of the firſt way, how it ought to be endeavoured, <hi>viz.</hi> privatively.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Now poſitively, and that two manner of wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By a generall Humiliation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By a particular Reformation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By a generall humiliation, When all of us from the higheſt unto the loweſt, ſhall like the
<note n="o" place="margin">Ionah 3.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Ninivites,</hi> preſent our ſelves before God, in ſackcloth and aſhes, and ply him with our ſighs and teares, our faſtings and prayers, which are
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſunt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma coeleſtia quae ſtare &amp; perſeverare fortiter faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, hoc ſunt munimenta ſptritualia &amp; tela divina quae protigunt nos. Cypr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1.</note> the ſpirituall weapons, wee alone can truſt unto, and the proper armour of a Chriſtian Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, to fight againſt the fearfull combinations, of the Churches powerfull and vigilant enemies. The Lord requires this at our hands, when we deſire great things to be wrought for us, he muſt and will be ſought unto, in the uſe of this meanes: At all times we ought to
<note n="q" place="margin">Macah. 6.8.</note> walke humbly with our God; in times of proſperitie, in times of greateſt joy; but eſpecially in ſuch times as theſe, now this grace is chiefly called for; when our crying ſinnes have awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened Gods juſtice, and broken the Viall of his anger over our heads, inſomuch, that the drops of bloud hang hoovering in the ayre, like clouds of vengeance, ready to breake downe upon us; when the darke and miſtie fogges of wickedneſſe, are gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111291:26"/>from ſundry places, threatning ſome great tempeſt of thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring and lightning, inſomuch, that wee have juſt cauſe to feare a black and diſmall day, a bloudy day of invaſion and utter deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion neere at hand. Now, (if ever) wee have need to humble our ſelves, that if poſſible, the ſtrong winde of our devotions, together with the ſwift gale of our ſighes and teares, may cleare the skie, and ſo diſpell thoſe cloudy vapours in ſuch ſort, as that they ſhall not fall upon us. This is the courſe propoſed unto us; the moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall meanes for the averting of judgement, and the obteining of mercy: This will flie to the Heavens, and peirce the clouds, and not be terrified with the height, nor yet frighted with the frownes of juſtice; therefore the Saints in their greateſt ſtreits and ſtrongeſt oppoſitions, have betaken themſelves unto this meanes. The
<note n="r" place="margin">Iudg. 20.26.</note> 
               <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> when they were diſtreſſed, for the murther of their men, which were ſlaine by the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> went up to the houſe of God, and there ſpent an whole day, <hi>in weeping, fasting, and prayer.
<note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Chro. 20.3.</note> Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> commanded a publick faſt to be kept, when the enemies of the <hi>Jewes</hi> invaded his Kingdome. So did
<note n="t" place="margin">Nehem. 9.1.</note> 
               <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> of purpoſe to turne away the vengeance which might juſtly have befallen them, for marrying of ſtrange wives.</p>
            <p>This kinde of humiliation was exerciſed by
<note n="u" place="margin">Exod. 34.28.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes,
<note n="w" place="margin">1 King 19.8.</note> Elias,</hi> and our
<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 4.2.</note> Saviour Chriſt, at ſuch times as when great matters were to be attempted by them, It is that, which in theſe dangerous times of ours, both God, our King and Countrey, have called upon us to performe. The gliſtering ornaments of Courtly robes, have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy been changed into mourning weeds; The great King of <hi>England</hi> (as ſometime the King of
<note n="y" place="margin">Ionah 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>Ninive</hi>) hath aroſe from his throne, and ſtript himſelfe of his coſtly rayment; the Princes, the Nobles, and Peeres, have already moyſtned this way with their teares, and put on with all their force of zealous prayers: You in the Citie, and wee in the Countrey, have <hi>ſate in aſhes, and girded our ſelves with ſackcloath;</hi> how farre wee have prevailed, the God of heaven onely knowes: My charitie gives me to thinke, that in the great and ſolemne dayes of your humiliation, <hi>you humbled your ſelves
<note n="z" place="margin">2 Chron. 33.12.</note> greatly before the God of your Fathers; and cryed
<note n="a" place="margin">Ionah 3.8.</note> mightily unto him;</hi> with holy eagerneſſe, yee devoure thoſe faſts, and are well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with the auſteritie of that pious penitence; It is the comfort of your ſoule to be perſwaded, you ſhall prevaile with God; the very thoughts of the continuance of his frownes upon you, were enough (with
<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 4.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Cain</hi>) to make you caſt your countenance downe to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111291:26"/>the ground. If ſucceſſe prove not anſwerable to your hopes, there is yet required a greater meaſure of humiliation;
<note n="c" place="margin">Joel 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>Let the Bridegroome goe forth of his Chamber, &amp; the Bride out of her Cloſet;</hi> Let every man hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelfe in his own familie, betwixt himſelfe and his own Spirit, himſelfe and his own houſhold, (no further I durſt not warrant you, as to aſſume that prerogative to your ſelves, by gathering (when you pleaſe) an open aſſembly, to ſanctifie a publick faſt, to call to ſackcloth &amp; mourning, before the Magiſtrate have decreed it; this were to deny <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due, to preſcribe a ſervice contrary to the preſident of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 7.6. 2 Chron. 20.3. Ezra 8.21. Heſt. 4.16. 1 Kin. 24.8. Ioel 3.15.</note> Scriptures, and to teach a point of diſcord and confuſion, which within a Chriſtian Common-wealth, muſt carefully be avoyded) one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with your ſelves, in your own private domeſticall charge, (if need require) weekly uſe the benefit of this meanes;
<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 55.17.</note> 
               <hi>Cry aloud unto God, evening and morning, and at noone;</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 32.24, 26.</note> Wreſtle with him (as <hi>Jacob</hi> did) never let him goe, untill you have obtained the bleſſing; be your reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution as the <hi>Shunamites</hi> was when ſhee ſpake to <hi>Eliſha,
<note n="g" place="margin">2 Kin. 4.30.</note> As the Lord liveth, I will not leave thee.</hi> And if through the continuance of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the time ſhall require it, you may in a godly and modeſt manner, as humble remembrancers, ſolicite Authority, for a more frequent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of this dutie, and in your private devotions deſire the Lord to move their hearts, to proclaime that which ſhall be truly pleaſing in his eyes, that a whole burnt offering might be made unto the Lord, from the higheſt to the loweſt, a ſolemne dedication of every perſon and ſtate, throughout the whole Kingdom; that ſo every one in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall may more frequently concur and agree, in ſeeking remedy againſt our eminent danger; oh! what a pleaſing ſacrifice will this be unto God, how may it prevaile with him, to cauſe him to alter his purpoſe &amp; change his determination, concerning our deſtruction. <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to
<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 33.3, 4. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Eſau,</hi> altered the purpoſe of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and prevailed with him, it cauſed his very bowells to yearne, he was not the man that he was before; our ſubmiſſion hath ever annexed the melting and relenting, or (to uſe the Scripture phraſe) the
<note n="i" place="margin">Iſa. 63.15.</note> 
               <hi>ſounding of the
<note n="k" place="margin">Ier. 31.20.</note> bowells of the Lord;</hi> How reſolved ſoever he was to deſtroy <hi>Ninive</hi> (as appeareth in the Meſſage of the Prophet,
<note n="l" place="margin">Ionah 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Yet fortie dayes and Ninive ſhall be deſtroyed,</hi>) upon their generall humiliation it is ſaid,
<note n="m" place="margin">Verſ 10.</note> 
               <hi>God repented of the evill, that he had ſaid, that he would doe unto them, and he did it not.</hi> So after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to peeviſh <hi>Jonah,
<note n="n" place="margin">Cap. 4.11.</note> Should not I ſpare Ninive that great Citie, wherein are ſix ſcore thouſand perſons, not diſcerning between the right hand and the left.</hi> It is never in vaine to humble our ſelves, and call upon the Lord; the promiſe is,
<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 91.15.</note> 
               <hi>He will heare and deliver.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:111291:27"/>
            <p>Thoſe many good things, which by this meanes the Saints have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, may confirm us in the truth of it, (not to inſtance in <hi>Moſes, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua, Samuel, David,</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi>) by this meane
<note n="p" place="margin">2 King. 19.15.</note> 
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did turne that evill thought of <hi>Senacherib</hi> away from his Land and people; by theſe very weapons S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> oppugned his enemies; by this the good
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Conſtant. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtantius</hi> was ſaid to ſtrengthen his familie, and
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, his Son, did hereby fortifie all his Empire. How frequent were the primitive Saints in this meanes, againſt the Propoſitions of Chriſt and his Goſpell; When <hi>Arrius</hi> the Heretique (having an injunction of the Emperour for it) would needs come to the Communion;
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Socrat. hiſt. Eccleſ.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note> 
               <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the good Biſhop, did betake himſelfe to abſtinence, and faſting, did pray Chriſt Jeſus to take the matter into his owne hand, which accordingly was graunted unto him, to the deſtruction of the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique both in body and ſoule. Long ſince this, in later ages that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy member of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Martin Luther</hi> perceiving the doctrine of the Goſpell to be brought into a great ſtreite; ſtrong oppoſition being made againſt it, by the enemies thereof; he flies to his God, layes hold upon him by faith, and offereth violence to him by prayer; never lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth wreſtling with him untill he received co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort from him; at length riſing up cheerfully from his devotion, comes out of his cloſet trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly to his fellow-labourers, ſaying, <hi>Vicimus,</hi> We have overcome. At which time,
<note n="u" place="margin">Ioh. Sleidan. in Comment.</note> 
               <hi>Sleidan</hi> obſerveth, that there came out a Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from <hi>Charles</hi> 5 that none ſhould be further moleſted for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Goſpell. Every age affordeth many examples of Gods gracious aſſiſtance in the conſcionable uſe of this meanes, when great matters are to be effected. Motives ſufficient (in theſe times) to ſtirre us up to the performance of this dutie; which is the firſt I here poſitively commend unto your Chriſtian practice, <hi>viz.</hi> A generall humiliation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By a particular Reformation, when every man and woman in their own private perſons, ſhall endeavour to amend what they finde amiſſe, and reform themſelves in their perſonall corruptions; ſo eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one amending one, it will be a ſpeedie way to accompliſh the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of all. Now what theſe corruptions are, you yourſelves beſt know, your own conſciences being throughly acquainted with the ſundrie paſſages of your converſation: for my part, I could be content, <hi>not to tell them in
<note n="w" place="margin">2 Sam. 1.20. Micah 1.10.</note> Gath, nor yet declare them in the ſtreets of Askelon;</hi> but the Lord willeth that we
<note n="x" place="margin">Iſa. 58.1.</note> 
               <hi>crie aloud and ſpare not, that we lift up our voice like a trumpet, and ſhew his people their tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the houſe of Jacob their ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He hath ſomewhat againſt every inhabitant of this great Iſland,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:111291:27"/>even from
<note n="y" place="margin">Which were the utmoſt Townes boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Land of <hi>Paleſtina</hi> from North to South. <hi>Dan.</hi> viz. <hi>Ab Aquilone &amp; Berſheba ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Meridiem. Petr. Martyr. in</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.20. <hi>&amp; Piſcat. Schol. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Berſheba,</hi> from the point of <hi>Catneſſe</hi> to the cape of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Burien,</hi> from the King that ſitteth in the throne, to the maid that grindeth at the Mill, from the Cedar to the ſhrub, from the Eagle to the Wren, from the higheſt to the loweſt, from the youngeſt to the oldeſt, from the richeſt to the pooreſt, we have all
<note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 6.12.</note> corrupted our wayes; <hi>Aegrotat humanum genus</hi> (as
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Serm.</hi> 6. <hi>de verb. Domini.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks) we are all ſick with ſin, and overgrown with heaps of vices, as was
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cicer. Tuſc. quaest. lib.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Archimedes</hi> tombe with thorns, when <hi>Cicero</hi> came to viſit it.</p>
            <p>I cannot rip up, neither am I acquainted with all the particulars of our national ſins; time and your patience would prevent me, if I ſhould but reckon up ſo many as deſerve our ſpeedieſt reformation; as our tranſcendent pride, unmercifull oppreſſion, cruell extortion, over-mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull connivence to ſin, open prophaneneſſe, waſtefull prodigalitie, inſatiable avarice, ſymonaicall ſacriledge, unbridled luxurie, beaſtly drunkenneſſe, bloodie treacherie ſlanderous detraction, cunning fraud, envious underminings, ambitious temporizings, and ſuch like, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with coldneſſe in zeal, contempt of Gods Word, profanation of his Sabbaths, neglect of his Sacraments, and what not? to name all were impoſſible. We need rather tears to bewail them, then a tongue to report them; for every one of them threatens our deſtruction, thwarts our hopes, hinders our proceedings, diſturbes our peace, heartens our enemies, diſplayes our weakneſſe, and will in the end (if not amended) make us a fearfull ſpectacle of Gods juſtice. Oh blame me not for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the wretched nakedneſſe of this ſinfull Nation; I know indeed complaints, howſoever they may be juſt, yet they are ſeldome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; but now, not more unpleaſing then neceſſarie; and therefore I could yet be more particular, Is it not before the Lord, whom I ſpeak? Is not Gods hand in thoſe judgements which hang over our heads? Is it for nothing that we are circuled round with ſo many eminent dangers? that the glory of this our Kingdom (which not long ago was ſo reſplendent, that it dazled the eyes of ſuch as were neer or about it;) hath been of late ſo darkly ecclipſed? that God goes not forth with our Armies, but ſuffers our enemies to prevail? that our friends won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and our foes rejoyce at our ill ſucceſſe? hiſſing and clapping their hands to ſee our glory ſwallowed up? that our own ſwords are daily threatned to be drawn againſt us, and the unnatural brood of our own neſts, readie to bite out our bellies? All which are infallible tokens that God is highly diſpleaſed with us: is there not a cauſe then that we enquire? that I crie? Do I alone ſpeak of theſe things? have not the Turtles of this land in every corner therof, groaned out the ſad tunes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:111291:28"/>of woe and miſerie? Is it not the uſuall ſubject of your publique Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this Citie? hath not God ſo guided the hearts and tongues of his faithfull Miniſters, that almoſt all of them (even as one man) do conſtantly crie out (with that
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſeph. li.</hi> 7. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e bell. lud.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.12.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſus</hi> the ſon of <hi>Anani</hi> a little before the deſtruction of Jeruſalem) wo to <hi>England</hi> and the Inhabitants thereof, by reaſon of ſuch outragious wickednes, as doth every where abound amongſt them. Theſe ſad complaints occaſioned by our preſumptuous ſins, are manifeſt ſymptomes of ſome greater evill that will certainly follow; as the cracking of the houſe is the fore-warning of his fall: theſe be but the flaſhing lightnings, the thunderbolt of deſtruction will come ſuddenly after, unleſſe by our repentance and reformation, we houſe our ſelves under the wings of Gods protection from the danger.</p>
            <p>Oh, let us then in time bethink our ſelves of ſome remedie,
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mittamus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reces &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heymas cordis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gatos. Cypr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an. li.</hi> 4. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 4.</note> diſpatch meſſengers to heaven and meet God by the way, make an attonement with him before the fulneſſe of his wrath break in upon us: yet there is ſpace and opportunity (and not more then) enough; the manifeſt breaches threatning the deſtruction of this Kingdom, may yet be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, upon our amendment; as ſome reaſonable coſt will ſet to rights the beginning ruins of a decaying houſe, which when it is once dropt down with danger about our eares, will hardly be re-edified. Let every one in his ſeverall place and calling, put his hand to this work; ceaſe any more from complaints, and fall all to amendment.</p>
            <p>You that be Magiſtrates, who ſit in the ſtearn of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth in the ſeat of Juſtice, ceaſe to beak your ſelves, like
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 36.22.</note> 
               <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> before the fire of eaſe and reſt; let not the Sword of Juſtice ruſt in the ſcabbard of connivence, when God, your King, your Countrey, cals to have it drawn againſt the enemies of our peace; do not ſtand like St. <hi>Georges</hi> picture, with your hands up, and never ſtrike; rather reaſon with your ſelves, as ſometimes the Orator did againſt <hi>Cateline;</hi> Did <hi>Publius Scipio,</hi> a private man, kill <hi>Tiberius Gracchus,</hi> but lightly weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſtate of the Common-wealth; and ſhall we that are Conſul, let <hi>Cateline</hi> alone, deſirous to lay waſte all the world with ſlaughter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and firings. Let it be your care with <hi>David,
<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal 101.8.</note> Early to deſtroy the wicked of the land, and to cut off all wicked doers from the City of the Lord:</hi> give a down-right blowe to thoſe offenſive evils, which cry for a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſtroke, that they may no more ſtalke by you, much leſſe ſtare upon you uncontrolled. For this purpoſe walk the ſtreets, ſearch all diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered houſes, and conſtrain the prophane to frequent the ſanctuaries; to hear the good word of the Lord. In your own perſons, follow the directions of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,
<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa 33.15.</note> Walk righteouſly, and ſpeak uprightly,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111291:28"/>deſpiſe the gain of oppreſſions, ſhake your hands from holding of bribes, leſt your ears be ſtopped from hearing of blood, and your eyes ſhut from ſeeing of evill.</hi> Let not gold weigh heavier then <hi>Naboths</hi> wrongs in the ſchools of Juſtice; leſt you ſell your connivence (and withall your conſcience) when and where you ſhould give puniſhment.</p>
            <p>You that are Miniſters and meſſengers of God,
<note n="h" place="margin">Ioel 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>Weep between the porch and the Altar:</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ier. 22.20. Hoſea 5.8.</note> Cry aloud againſt your own ſins and the ſins of others; fear not any mans perſon, nor yet ſpare any mans profeſſion, teacher nor hearer, Prince nor people, Ruler nor Subject, rich nor poore, your Commiſſion ſtretcheth it ſelf as far as Chriſt, redemption to all ſorts in generall; Be not like thoſe foure hundred prophets men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned the 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.6. ſlaves and vaſſals to any mans affections, preaching no otherwiſe then the beſt man in your Pariſh would have you, deliver the <hi>word of God plainly, powerfully, in
<note n="k" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.2.</note> ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon;</hi> let your life and doctrine agree together (as it was ſometime ſaid of <hi>Origen,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Quale habuit verbumtale habuit vitam.</note> his life was anſwerable to his doctrine) beat down the body of ſin in your ſelves as well as in others: ſuffer not your gifts to be wrapped up in an idle brain without practiſe, as
<note n="m" place="margin">1 Sam. 21.9.</note> 
               <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſword was in a cloth without uſe; nor yet the fountain of your knowledge like
<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 29.10.</note> 
               <hi>Labans</hi> Well, to be ſhut up with a great ſtone of ſecuritie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king either the Court with
<note n="o" place="margin">3 Ioh. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> or the Univerſitie with
<note n="p" place="margin">Ille Athenas profectius, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derto Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie captus eſt cujus ea fuit, &amp;c. Ex Suida.</note> 
               <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anthes,</hi> a ſanctuary for your idleneſſe; but rather paſſe your time with holy
<note n="q" place="margin">Hieron. epiſt. ad Marcel.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> in conference with God, and practiſe of holy duties, as in reading, or meditating, or praying, or conferring, or counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or comforting, or writing, or preaching.</p>
            <p>You that are called to the ſtudy of the Laws, (for ſuch alſo I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to tread on the pavement of this ſacred place, and to ſit within the compaſſe of theſe conſecrated wals) your noble Science and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is commendable, none but
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anabaptiſta arguunt illici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp;c. Vide Paraeum in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor. c.</hi> 3.7.</note> Anabaptiſts will deny a Chriſtian that liberty of ſeeking remedy from you, when injurious perſons ſhall grow worſe by forbearance, and ground their inſolence upon others patience. Let not favour nor affection over-ſway you in your places; but rather count him an enemie that will alledge friendſhip to pervert juſtice Go as far as you can in offices of love and ſervice to your friends and betters, <hi>Salvis pietate &amp; juſtitia</hi> but not a ſtep further for a world: if you ſeek to
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Galat. 1.10.</note> pleaſe men beyond this, you cannot be the ſervants of God. Do not hide the native face of your Clients cauſe by ſhufling plainneſſe into difficulties; you ſhould employ your beſt knowledge in untying the knots of the Law, and be as Antropoſes to cut off the threed of controverſies between man and man, and not feed thoſe that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:111291:29"/>come unto you for counſell, with golden hopes and ſugred words, and large promiſes, while in the mean time like <hi>Lacheſis,</hi> ye draw in length the threed of contention, uſing unneceſſary delayes, and poſting off the matter from Tearm to Tearm, from Court to Court, from yeer to yeer, dealing with your beſt cauſes, as unconſcionable Chirurgions are wont to do with ſore legs, hold them long in hand, not for the difficultie of the cure, but for preſent hope of future gain.</p>
            <p>But rather harden your faces, and ſtrengthen your reſolutions with an holy obſtinacie, againſt theſe and all other like temptations; ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you ſhall further the Reformation, bring glory unto God, good unto his Church, ſafetie unto your Prince and State, peace and quiet unto the Common-wealth wherein you live; and laſt of all, a crown of bleſſings upon your head for ever.</p>
            <p>You that are Merchants and Tradeſmen, do not like thoſe in
<note n="t" place="margin">Amos 8.5.</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> grudge the Lord of his day, through the longing thoughts of your own Market, nor yet falſifie the ballances by deceit, nor <hi>make the ephah ſmall, nor the ſhekel great.</hi> Let not deſire of profit in over-prizing, nor yet pride of wit in over-reaching, be the main principles of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; do not prejudice your conſcience, by putting off your
<note n="u" place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> refuſe wares, under a vain pretext of <hi>caveat emptor:</hi> ſell not your oaths and proteſtations, and withall your ſouls, by venting off your bad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities; do not through a dark window, nor yet by the help of an impudent tongue, deal unconſcionable, when as you tell your cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, you ask but reaſonable; take not advantage of any mans neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities; and ſo thruſt your wares upon him, which have ſtood longer by you then the yeers of an Apprentiſhip; watch not opportunitie to abuſe the ſimple plainneſſe of your honeſt cuſtomers, whoſe apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions come far ſhort of yours in the driving of a bargain. But in all your trading, ſo carry your ſelves, as in the parting with your commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, you may ſtill keep the peace of a good conſcience.</p>
            <p>You that are Maſters of families, and petty Kings and Prieſts in your own houſes, look to your charges, with <hi>David</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Pſal. 101.6.</note> fix your <hi>eyes upon the faithfull in the Land,</hi> that ſuch may dwell with you, and ſerve you; Be there within the compaſſe of your own regiment, a
<note n="x" place="margin">2 King. 5.25.</note> lying <hi>Jehazi,</hi> or a
<note n="y" place="margin">2 Sam. 16.3.</note> backbiting <hi>Ziba,</hi> an
<note n="z" place="margin">Luk. 16.6, 7.</note> unjuſt Steward, or a
<note n="a" place="margin">Matth. 25.26.30.</note> wicked and unprofitable ſervant, an Atheiſt, a Papiſt, a ſwearer, a prophaner of the Sabbaths, a ſwaggerer, an uncleane perſon, or ſuch like, endeavour by admonition and correction to reclaim them, and if they prove incorrigible, with
<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 35.2.</note> 
               <hi>Jacob</hi> cleanſe and purge your families of them, doe not ſuffer ſuch to
<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 101.7.</note> dwell in your houſe; Let no corruption be within your compaſſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:111291:29"/>connived a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, nor yet unpurged; beware of giving ill example unto ſuch as are under your charge, through your looſe converſation, but rather endeavour to the utmoſt of your power, (by family-duties)
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>De ſalute corum qui in domo tua ſunt ſolicitus ac pervigie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt as, quia pro omnibus tibi ſubiectis ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Domino reddes. Aug. de ſalut. do cum ca.</hi> 29.</note> to ſeeke their ſpirituall edification;
<note n="e" place="margin">Deut. 6.7.</note> talke of the Lawes of GOD when you ſit in your houſe, and with
<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 18.19.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> command your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſervants to keep the way of the Lord; ſo ſhall you not onely love their bodies here on earth, but one day meet their ſouls in heave.</p>
            <p>In a word, Let every one that loves his Nation, that favours Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that wiſheth continuance of the Goſpell, the proſperous procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Parliament, peace &amp; proſperitie unto the Kingdome; reforme himſelfe in his converſation, and conſecrate his own hands, to the pulling downe of the Kingdom of ſin; Downe with it, down with it, even to the ground. And this is the ſecond poſitive dutie which wee muſt endeavour to performe, if we deſire to further the Reformation, <hi>viz.</hi> A particular amendment in every perſon.</p>
            <p>But now I feare me, through too much prolixitie of ſpeech, I have over-boldly entrencht upon your patience; the time is more than paſt, &amp; it is moſt fitting we ſhould draw to an end; The zeale of Gods glory, and the heartie deſire of my Countreys welfare, hath hitherto enlarged my diſcourſe (further then I had thought) againſt the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of the time, the maine enemies of God and this Kingdome; Let mee crave your attendance but to one thing more, and ſo I ſhall diſmiſſe you for this preſent; and that is this:</p>
            <p>Suppoſe the queſtion which once was made by the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> ſhould now be propounded in this great Aſſembly,
<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 34.12.</note> 
               <hi>What man is he that deſireth life, and loveth many dayes, that he may ſee good,</hi> or that <hi>he may ſee good dayes</hi> (as the
<note n="h" place="margin">1 Pet. 3.10.</note> Apoſtle expreſſeth it, following the <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint</hi>) <hi>(i.e.)</hi> good and quiet dayes;
<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aynſworth Annotat. in Pſal.</hi> 3.4.</note> dayes of proſperitie, pleaſure, and comfort, &amp;c. Such dayes wherein your conſciences ſhall be no more enthralled to the ordinances of men; wherein your zeale ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by ſound knowledge; wherein your Religion ſhall be reformed by ſtatutes of the higheſt God; Such dayes, wherein peace being once more ſetled amongſt us, we may
<note n="k" place="margin">2 Sam. 7.1.</note> 
               <hi>every one without feare, ſit under our own Vines and Figtrees;</hi> Such dayes wherein our Merchants may chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully trade abroad, &amp; bring home
<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 104.15.</note> 
               <hi>Wines to glad our hearts, and Oyle to make our face to ſhine;</hi> Such dayes wherein our Artificers may ſit at home and ſing in their ſhops; wherein our husbandmen chearfully following the plough, <hi>may
<note n="m" place="margin">Iames 5.7.</note> ſow their Corne in hope, and reape with joy;</hi> Such dayes wherein <hi>our
<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 144.12.</note> ſons may be as plants growen up in their youth; and our daughters may be as corner ſtones, poliſhed after the ſimilitude of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:111291:30"/>a Palace;</hi> Such dayes wherein our
<note n="o" place="margin">Verſ. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>garners may be full,</hi> affording all manner of ſtore; <hi>wherein our ſheepe may bring forth thouſands, and ten thouſands in our ſtreets; wherein our Oxen may be ſtrong to labour; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there may be no breaking in, nor going out; no complaining in our ſtreets, &amp;c.</hi> I ſay, if the queſtion ſhould be demanded; Who would deſire to ſee theſe dayes? I doubt not, but wee ſhould ſuddenly heare a whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering noiſe proceed from the joyfull hearts of many here aſſembled. I would, ſayes one, I would, ſayes another; yea, a loud cry, with an unanimous conſent of all your voyces, even from the Magiſtrate in the Pew, to the Water-bearer in the Bell-fry; I, I, I, defire to ſee it.</p>
            <p>Be ſilent then a while; you have heard how this may be done; be not covetous, nor ſuperſtitious, nor lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tious, nor yet run before thoſe appointed in the reformation; Labour to be ſetled in the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; be not divided in your affections, diſſent not about your Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers; humble your ſelves mightily before God, by faſting, by praw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; amend every one your evill wayes.</p>
            <p>Then will the Lord be mercifull to this Land; he will quickly turne the ſower looks of an angry and ſin-revenging Judge, into the ſmiling countenance of a mild and gentle Father; he will take the rod which he hath prepared for us, and burne it in the fire; he will ſtay the ſtroke, which is now begun in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and reſtore to them and us, our helpes againe: All things ſhall proſper with us, and nothing ſhall ſtop the current of his bleſſings from us; he will confound our enemies, by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointing their hopes, and breaking their power in ſunder; he will waſh away all the dreggs of Popery and ſuperſtition, which now op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe &amp; trouble the ſtate of the Church of Chriſt; he will ſubdue Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, with all his Adherents, and ſo overthrow his purpoſes, that his very memory ſhall be had in confuſion. Of his liberall goodneſſe, he will give us more of ſuch ayde and helpe, as ſhall be needfull to work the through reformation of our State in generall, and of every one of us in particular; He will goe on with that bleſſed worke begun in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and increaſe the good gifts of his holy Spirit, upon the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie Members of both Houſes; furniſh them with ſuch a meaſure of knowledge, zeale, diligence, &amp; holy conſtancy, as that they ſhall cleare the paſſage of the glorious Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, from all diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance: build up the profeſſion of Gods pure Religion in ſinceritie, and ſtabliſh the civill regiment of this Common-wealth in peace &amp; equity.</p>
            <p>The which God of Heaven grant for his mercies ſake, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous for his merits ſake, the Holy Ghoſt the comforter, for his names ſake, to whom be all praiſe, power, and glory, now and for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:111291:30"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
